<d:chapter version="5.0" xmlns:d="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <?xml-stylesheet href="../css/style.css" type="text/css"?>
    <?dbhtml filename="std/index.html" ?>
    <d:title>The C Standard Library</d:title>
    <d:para>This chapter and rest of book eflects chapter 7 of
    n1124.pdf. This chapter begins with assert.h. We will see three
    parts of each function/macro as much as possible. From
    specification, compiler and example point of view in that
    order.</d:para>
    <d:sect1>
      <d:title>Introduction</d:title>
      <d:sect2>
	<d:title>Definition of Terms</d:title>
	<d:para>A <d:emphasis role="italic">string</d:emphasis> is a contiguous
	sequence of characters terminated by and including the first null
	character. The term <d:emphasis role="italic">multibyte
	string</d:emphasis> is sometimes used instead to emphasize special
	processing given to multibyte characters contained in the string or to
	avoid confusion with a <d:emphasis role="italic">wide
	string</d:emphasis>. A <d:emphasis role="italic">pointer to a
	string</d:emphasis> is a pointer to its initial (lowest addressed)
	character. The length of a string is the number of bytes preceding the
	null character and the <d:emphasis role="italic">value of a
	string</d:emphasis> is the sequence of the values of the contained
	characters, in order.</d:para>
	<d:para>The <d:emphasis role="italic">decimal-point
	character</d:emphasis> is the character used by functions that convert
	floating-point numbers to or from character sequences to denote the
	beginning of the fractional part of such character
	sequences.<d:footnote><d:para>The functions that make use of the
	decimal-point character are the numeric conversion functions (14.20.1,
	14.24.4.1) and the formatted input/output functions (14.19.6,
	14.24.2).</d:para></d:footnote>  It is represented in the text and
	examples by a period, but may be changed by the
	<d:code>setlocale</d:code> function.</d:para>
	<d:para>A <d:emphasis role="italic">null wide character</d:emphasis> is
	a wide character with code value zero.</d:para>
	<d:para>A <d:emphasis role="italic">wide string</d:emphasis> is a
	contiguous sequence of wide characters terminated by and including the
	first null wide character. A <d:emphasis role="italic">pointer to a
	wide string</d:emphasis> is a pointer to its initial (lowest addressed)
	wide character. The <d:emphasis role="italic">length of a wide
	string</d:emphasis> is the number of wide characters preceding the null
	wide character and the <d:emphasis role="italic">value of a wide
	string</d:emphasis> is the sequence of code values of the contained
	wide characters, in order.</d:para>
	<d:para>A <d:emphasis role="italic">shift sequence</d:emphasis> is a
	contiguous sequence of bytes within a multibyte string that
	(potentially) causes a change in shift state. A shift sequence shall
	not have a corresponding wide character; it is instead taken to be an
	adjunct to an adjacent multibyte character.<d:footnote><d:para>For
	state-dependent encodings, the values for <d:code>MB_CUR_MAX</d:code>
	and <d:code>MB_LEN_MAX</d:code> shall thus be large enough to count all
	the bytes in any complete multibyte character plus at least one
	adjacent shift sequence of maximum length. Whether these counts provide
	for more than one shift sequence is the implementation’s
	choice.</d:para></d:footnote></d:para>
      </d:sect2>
      <d:sect2>
	<d:title>Standard Headers</d:title>
	<d:para>Each library function is declared, with a type that includes a
	prototype, in a header,<d:footnote><d:para>A header is not necessarily
	a source file, nor are the &lt; and > delimited sequences in header
	names necessarily valid source file names.</d:para></d:footnote>
	whose contents are made available by the <d:code>#include</d:code>
	preprocessing directive. The header declares a set of related
	functions, plus any necessary types and additional macros needed to
	facilitate their use. Declarations of types described in this clause
	shall not include type qualifiers, unless explicitly stated
	otherwise.</d:para>
	<d:para>The standard headers are:</d:para>
	<d:screen>&amp;lt;assert.h>  &amp;lt;inttypes.h> &amp;lt;signal.h>  &amp;lt;stdlib.h>
&amp;lt;complex.h> &amp;lt;iso646.h>   &amp;lt;stdarg.h>  &amp;lt;string.h>
&amp;lt;ctype.h>   &amp;lt;limits.h>   &amp;lt;stdbool.h> &amp;lt;tgmath.h>
&amp;lt;errno.h>   &amp;lt;locale.h>   &amp;lt;stddef.h>  &amp;lt;time.h>
&amp;lt;fenv.h>    &amp;lt;math.h>     &amp;lt;stdint.h>  &amp;lt;wchar.h>
&amp;lt;float.h>   &amp;lt;setjmp.h>   &amp;lt;stdio.h>   &amp;lt;wctype.h></d:screen>
      </d:sect2>
    </d:sect1>
</d:chapter>
