<d:chapter version="5.0" xmlns:d="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <?xml-stylesheet href="../css/style.css" type="text/css"?>
    <?dbhtml filename="fs/index.html" ?>
    <d:title>Following Specification</d:title>
    <d:para>At this point of time I would like to look back and refer to C99 specification n1124.pdf
      located at <link xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
        xlink:href="http://www.open-std.org/jtc1/sc22/wg14/www/docs/n1124.png"
        >http://www.open-std.org/jtc1/sc22/wg14/www/docs/n1124.pdf</link>, which, is the C99
      specification with me. Since my thoughts are random in nature I will try to follow the
      organization of content given in the specification. This treatment of C99 is very tightly
      coupled with compiler(clang) and specification. If someone says that a book can be written by
      ignoring any of these two then I will be the last person to believe that.:P However, note that
      I will not include all the contents of specification and will exclude some of very obvious and
      trivial sections/subsections. The following terms, definitions and symbols have come from
      specification, however, some are omitted for the sake of conciseness. When I will repeat the
      specification at times I will do a verbatim copy just for quick reference and then add an
      explanation to that. Believe me you can learn most of the language just by studying the
      specification itself. Chapter no. 2, 3 and 4 will have material which may have redundant
      material discussed elsewhere in the book. Note that specification is directed more at compiler
      writers rather than at developers. However, it still covers a lot of ground and is also
      helpful to understand the nature of different compilers as where they can go in different
      directions.</d:para>
    <d:sect1>
      <d:title>Terms, Definitions and Symbols</d:title>
      <d:orderedlist>
        <d:listitem>
          <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">access:</d:emphasis> &lt;execution-time action&gt; to read
            or modify the value of an object.</d:para>
          <d:para>NOTE 1: Where only one of these two actions is meant, “read” or “modify” is
            used.</d:para>
          <d:para>NOTE 2: “Modify” includes the case where the new value being stored is the same as
            the previous value.</d:para>
          <d:para>NOTE 3: Expressions that are not evaluated do not access objects.</d:para>
          <d:para>There are two parts of any program. Data and instruction. Programs are stored in
            file on some non-volatile storage for example, hard disk drive, CD, DVD, tape drive.
            When they are executed from non-volatile storage they are transferred to some volatile
            storage typically RAM (Random Access Memory) of the computer. When a program is executed
            it becomes a living entity capable of doing something and sometimes also referred as
            process. So when the contents of RAM (henceforth referred as memory) is either read or
            written (it does not matter whether the value is same or new) to then it is defined as
            access. Here point to be noted is that the expressions which will not be evaluated do
            not access objects.</d:para>
          <d:para>There are certain issues with the term read and modify. One can ask it it the case
            that multiplication or division of a number with 1 modifies it or addition or
            subtraction of a number with 0 modifies it. The answer is yes on all these accounts.
            Similarly, you can ask if a bit-field is accessed then is it the case that the
            bit-fields sharing the storage in memory are also accessed. My answer would be yes. The
            reason is there is no way to get address of an individual bit and we get at least
            32-bits in one fetch cycle on a 32-bit processor.</d:para>
          <d:para>There can be various reasons why an expression is not evaluated. For
            example:</d:para>
          <d:itemizedlist>
            <d:listitem>
              <d:para>being part of a statement which is not executed probably because of
                conditional compilation,</d:para>
            </d:listitem>
            <d:listitem>
              <d:para>being part of a sub-expression whose evaluation is conditional on other
                sub-expressions within a full expression; this means the above point, and</d:para>
            </d:listitem>
            <d:listitem>
              <d:para>being an operand of the sizeof operator. sizeof operator never evaluates its
                operand or try to access them. It just computes their sizes and pass it
                along.</d:para>
            </d:listitem>
          </d:itemizedlist>
          <d:para>Also, consider the following
            program:<d:programlisting role="CLexer">#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

int main()
{
  int a=0, b=0, c=3, d=4;

  a = c + d;
  b = c + d;

  return 0;
}</d:programlisting></d:para>
          <d:para>In this code it is not necessary that data for c and d will be accessed for second
            addition.</d:para>
          <d:para>Also consider the following
            program:<d:programlisting role="CLexer">#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

typedef struct {
  volatile int x1:3;
  volatile int x2:3;
  volatile int x3:4;
  volatile int x4:1;
} S;

int main()
{
  int i = 7;
  S s;

  i = s.x2;

  return 0;
}</d:programlisting></d:para>
          <d:para>Now depending on whether system is little-endian or big-endian the storage of x2
            and x3 will be in different bytes. Also, this will change the way bytes are accessed
            when x2 is referred in memory. Many combinations are possible depending on processor
            architecture.</d:para>
        </d:listitem>
        <d:listitem>
          <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">alignment:</d:emphasis> requirement that objects of a
            particular type be located on storage boundaries with addresses that are particular
            multiples of a byte address.</d:para>
          <d:para>Say your program requires x bytes of memory then it will not be always given x
            bytes but something more. Say an object requires y bytes then it will be always greater
            or equal to y bytes. This is required so that objects are always located on storage
            boundaries that are particular multiples of byte address. The reason for this alignment
            lies in the efficiency of the operating system as a whole. As we know that on 32-bit
            systems data bus is 32 bits similarly on 64-bit systems it is 64 bits. This means in one
            fetch cycle (read up on this on some microprocessor or computer architecture book) only
            32-bits can be fetched. 32-bits means 4 bytes. Oops! I did not tell you about bits and
            bytes conversion. Not even nibble. However, since 4 bytes can be fetched in one cycle
            compiler tries to optimize the data in group of 4 bytes. Given below are some
            examples.<d:programlisting role="CLexer">/* Description: Demonstration of structure padding and memory alignment.*/

#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

typedef struct
{
  char a;
  int b;
}A;

typedef struct
{
  char a;
  int b;
  char c;
  char d;
  char e;
  int f;
}B;

typedef struct
{
  char x;
  char y;
  int z;
}C;

typedef struct
{
  char x;
  int z;
  char y;
}D;

int main()
{
  A a;
  B b;
  C c;
  D d;
  printf("Size of structure %c is %d\n",'A', sizeof(a));
  printf("Size of structure %c is %d\n",'B', sizeof(b));
  printf("Size of structure %c is %d\n",'C', sizeof(c));
  printf("Size of structure %c is %d\n",'D', sizeof(d));

  return 0;
}</d:programlisting></d:para>
          <d:para>the output is:<d:screen>Size of structure A is 8
Size of structure B is 16
Size of structure C is 8
Size of structure D is 12</d:screen></d:para>
          <d:para>Now let me ask you a question that how come size of C is 8 while size of D is 12
            while both structures contain same no. of similar elements. The answer lies in the order
            of elements. Further let us consider the following
            program:<d:programlisting role="CLexer">#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

typedef struct {
  char c;
  int j;
}t;

int main()
{
  t s1;

  s1.j = 4;
  s1.c = 5;

  printf("%p %p", &amp;s1.j, &amp;s1.c);

  return 0;
}</d:programlisting></d:para>
          <d:para>and the output
            is:<d:screen>0xbfc98f7c 0xbfc98f78</d:screen></d:para>
          <d:para>Now if you notice <d:code>0xbfc98f7c % 4</d:code> is 0 which is our alignment
            requirement. So, now you can see why structure C and D have different sizes.</d:para>
          <d:para>Another point worth noting is that certain processors allocate arrays on word
            boundaries which are power of 2. For example, a character array requiring x bytes will
            actually n bytes where x is not power of 2 and n is next power of 2 which is greater
            than x. Such optimizations are quite common in computers and you need to be aware of it
            to write efficient programs because you cannot make any assumptions about behavior of
            processor.</d:para>
        </d:listitem>
        <d:listitem>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"><emphasis role="bold"> argument:</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">actual argument</para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">actual parameter (deprecated)</para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">expression in the comma-separated list bounded
            by the parentheses in a function call expression, or a sequence of preprocessing tokens
            in the comma-separated list bounded by the parentheses in a function-like macro
            invocation.</para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">Sometimes they are also called actual
            parameters(in function definition) but as you can see in specification ISO/IEC 9899:TC2
            Section 3.3 this term is being deprecated. A function can have zero or more actual
            arguments and if they are more than one then each of them will be separated by a comma.
            These also apply to macros that is preprocessor directives when invoked like a function.
          </para>
        </d:listitem>
        <d:listitem>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"><emphasis role="bold"> behavior:</emphasis>
            external appearance or action</para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">By this term behavior the specification tries
            to categorize certain behavior which do not fall in other categories. For example, there
            are four more types of behaviors namely implementation-defined behavior, locale-specific
            behavior, undefined behavior and unspecified behavior. The term behavior categorizes
            external and those behaviors which do not fall under these four categories. External
            behavior includes mouse, keyboard and such.</para>
        </d:listitem>
        <d:listitem>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"><emphasis role="bold">implementation-defined
              behavior:</emphasis> unspecified behavior where each implementation documents how the
            choice is made.</para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">EXAMPLE An example of implementation-defined
            behavior is the propagation of the high-order bit when a signed integer is shifted
            right.</para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">When specification does not specify how a
            particular element of language should be implemented then programs use their logic to
            implement these things and sometimes it depends on hardware as well. Behavior of such
            elements is called implementation-defined-behavior. A full list of such behaviors is
            typically provided by the compiler.</para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">Consider the following example:</para>
          <d:programlisting role="CLexer">#include &lt;stdio.h>

int main()
{
  printf("%d %d\n", -2>>1, -1>>1);

  return 0;
}</d:programlisting>
          <d:para>and the output is:</d:para>
          <d:programlisting>-1 -1</d:programlisting>
        </d:listitem>
        <d:listitem>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"><emphasis role="bold"> locale-specific
              behavior:</emphasis> behavior that depends on local conventions of nationality,
            culture, and language that each implementation documents</para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">EXAMPLE An example of locale-specific behavior
            is whether the islower function returns true for characters other than the 26 lowercase
            Latin letters.</para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">Any behavior which changes when locale of the
            program changes will come under this category. The character e-acute is a lowercase
            letter in a Latin-1 locale, but not in the “C” locale. A full list of such behaviors is
            typically provided by the compiler.</para>
        </d:listitem>
        <d:listitem>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"><emphasis role="bold"> undefined
              behavior:</emphasis> behavior, upon use of a non-portable or erroneous program
            construct or of erroneous data, for which International Standard imposes no
            requirements.</para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">NOTE: Possible undefined behavior ranges from
            ignoring the situation completely with unpredictable results, to behaving during
            translation or program execution in a documented manner characteristic of the
            environment (with or without the issuance of a diagnostic message), to terminating a
            translation or execution (with the issuance of a diagnostic message).</para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">EXAMPLE An example of undefined behavior is
            the behavior on integer overflow.</para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">We will see more examples of these undefined
            behaviors as we go through the specification.</para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">It is very easy to say undefined behavior for
            specification but when a compiler programmer writes a compiler he cannot really say that
            our program is causing undefined behavior. Sometimes it will emit a warning but
            sometimes it will silently compile the program. However, then output of two compilers
            may not match. Even output of two different version of compilers may not match.</para>
        </d:listitem>
        <d:listitem>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"><emphasis role="bold"> unspecified
              behavior:</emphasis> use of an unspecified value, or other behavior where this
            International Standard provides two or more possibilities and imposes no further
            requirements on which is chosen in any instance.</para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">EXAMPLE An example of unspecified behavior is
            the order in which the arguments to a function are evaluated.</para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">We will more of these as we progress and list
            of all such behaviors is given in the appendix.</para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">It is different than undefined behavior but
            compiler writers are still free to to implement as they see fit. </para>
        </d:listitem>
        <d:listitem>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
            <emphasis role="bold">bit:</emphasis> unit of data storage in the execution environment
            large enough to hold an object that may have one of two values.</para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">NOTE It need not be possible to express the
            address of each individual bit of an object.</para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">The term bit was first coined by John Wilder
            Tukey who also coined the term software, best known for his work on fast Fourier
            transform(FFT). Note that base-2 is not the most efficient way to store the numbers but
            it is base-e. You can read about more on it in. [Hayes] Those who are from electronics
            background know that transistors operate in cut-off(very low voltage, high current) and
            saturation(high voltage, low current). These two states consume very less power. The
            other two states are active and reverse-active. However, power consumption is more.
            Therefore, just to save power there is a trade-off between compactness and power
            consumption. Usually, popular compilers like gcc or clang do not provide mechanism to
            sequence of bits. However, there is a compiler which allows bit-level addressing in
            registers if not memory. [Wegner] There are processors where data is not byte-aligned
            and some bit-level addressing is available as shown in [Nie] . </para>
        </d:listitem>
        <d:listitem>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
            <emphasis role="bold">byte:</emphasis> addressable unit of data storage large enough to
            hold any member of the basic character set of the execution environment.</para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">NOTE 1: It is possible to express the address
            of each individual byte of an object uniquely.</para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">NOTE 2: A byte is composed of a contiguous
            sequence of bits, the number of which is implementation-defined. The least significant
            bit is called the low-order bit; the most significant bit is called the high-order
            bit.</para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">As most of programmers will know that a byte
            is 8 bits. However, the term for 8 bits is octet as the term for 4 bits is nibble. This
            term is now so common for 8 bits that they are used interchangeably. Note that byte and
            char are different. byte is used to denote the storage while char is used to denote the
            type. We can say a 32-bit integer occupies 4 bytes but we cannot say the same in terms
            of char. [POSIX] defines a byte as an octet.</para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">Considering an integer which is a multi-byte
            type can have its bytes individually addressed. Even though it says that numbers of bits
            is implementation-defined on most systems this number is governed by CHAR_BIT macro
            which has a value of 8. </para>
        </d:listitem>
        <d:listitem>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"><emphasis role="bold">character:</emphasis>
            Member of a set of elements used for the organization, control, or representation of
            data.</para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">There are many character sets each capable of
            representing one language in this world. Sometimes they fit in a single byte while
            sometimes they do not and then we need more bytes to represent that kind of
            language.</para>
          <d:orderedlist numeration="upperroman">
            <d:listitem>
              <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">single-byte character: Bit representation
                that fits in a byte.</para>
            </d:listitem>
            <d:listitem>
              <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">multi-byte character: Sequence of one or
                more bytes representing a member of the extended character set of either the source
                or the execution environment.</para>
            </d:listitem>
            <d:listitem>
              <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">wide Character: Bit representation that
                fits in an object of type wchar_t, capable of representing any character in the
                current locale.</para>
            </d:listitem>
          </d:orderedlist>
          <d:para>A character is one the most primitive types of C programming language. On most
            machines its size is 1 byte. Even though void has also a size of 1 byte it is known as
            incomplete type and cannot be used to create an object.</d:para>
        </d:listitem>
        <d:listitem>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"><emphasis role="bold"> constraint:</emphasis>
            Restriction, either syntactic or semantic, by which the exposition of language elements
            is to be interpreted.</para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">There are certain restrictions imposed by the
            language through the standard which programmers must adhere to. Violation of these
            restrictions may lead to diagnostic messages being issued from the compiler. We will see
            such constraints throughout the standard. </para>
        </d:listitem>
        <d:listitem>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"><emphasis role="bold">correctly rounded
              result:</emphasis> Representation in the result format that is nearest in value,
            subject to the effective rounding mode, to what the result would be given unlimited
            range and precision.</para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">This is something which is very much related
            to floating-point numbers. Consider two representable numbers a and b. Now there can be
            infinite numbers between these two. However, there will be exactly one number which will
            lie in between them. If this number is not representable as per floating-point
            specification then the rounding of this number will depend on the current rounding mode
            in effect. IEEE specifies four rounding modes for rounding floating-point numbers. They
            are: <code>rd_near</code> (for rounding to the nearest), <code>rd_zero</code> (for
            rounding to zero), <code>rd_minf</code> (for rounding to minus infinity) and
              <code>rd_pinf</code> (for rounding to plus infinity). Consider the following program
            which shows all four rounding modes in action.</para>
          <d:programlisting role="CLexer">#include &lt;stdio.h>
#include &lt;stdlib.h>
#include &lt;fenv.h>

int main (int argc, char **argv)
{
  float x, y, z1, z2;

  x = 1.0;
  y = 1.0e-20;

  fesetround(FE_TONEAREST);
  z1 = x - y; z2 = y - x; z1 = z1 - x; z2 = z2 + x;
  printf("near, z1 = %17.10e, z2 = %17.10e \n", z1, z2);

  fesetround(FE_UPWARD);
  z1 = x - y; z2 = y - x; z1 = z1 - x; z2 = z2 + x;
  printf("minf, z1 = %17.10e, z2 = %17.10e \n", z1, z2);

  fesetround(FE_DOWNWARD);
  z1 = x - y; z2 = y - x; z1 = z1 - x; z2 = z2 + x;
  printf("pinf, z1 = %17.10e, z2 = %17.10e \n", z1, z2);

  fesetround(FE_TOWARDZERO);
  z1 = x - y; z2 = y - x; z1 = z1 - x; z2 = z2 + x;
  printf("zero, z1 = %17.10e, z2 = %17.10e \n", z1, z2);


return 0;
}</d:programlisting>
          <d:para>and the output is:</d:para>
          <d:screen>near, z1 =  0.0000000000e+00, z2 =  0.0000000000e+00
minf, z1 =  0.0000000000e+00, z2 =  5.9604644775e-08
pinf, z1 = -5.9604644775e-08, z2 = -0.0000000000e+00
zero, z1 = -5.9604644775e-08, z2 =  5.9604644775e-08</d:screen>
          <d:para>Note that you need to link with <d:code>-lm</d:code> for compilation of the
            program, just in case.</d:para>
        </d:listitem>
        <d:listitem>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"><emphasis role="bold"> diagnostic
              message:</emphasis> message belonging to an implementation-defined subset of the
            implementation’s message output.</para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">These refer to compilation-time warning or
            error messages produced by the compiler. Since the specification does not direct any
            particular way in which these diagnostic messages should be generated all compiler
            writers are free to do whatever suits their whim. For example, earlier gcc used to print
            only line numbers but now they also show column numbers where errors have occurred.
            clang goes one step further and produces colored output. </para>
        </d:listitem>
        <d:listitem>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"><emphasis role="bold">forward
              reference:</emphasis> Reference to a later subclause of International Standard that
            contains additional information relevant to this subclause.</para>
        </d:listitem>
        <d:listitem>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"><emphasis role="bold"
              >implementation:</emphasis> Particular set of software, running in a particular
            translation environment under particular control options, that performs translation of
            programs for, and supports execution of functions in, a particular execution
            environment.</para>
          <d:para>Here implementation means what we typically know as compiler. Note that it does
            not even say compiler. Even a C interpreter can be taken as an implementation. However,
            historically C has been a compiled language so we will mean implementation as compiler
            henceforth. Note that when you change compiler or even compiler options then you are
            changing the translation of code which means implementation has changed.</d:para>
        </d:listitem>
        <d:listitem>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"><emphasis role="bold"> implementation
              limit:</emphasis> Restriction imposed upon programs by the implementation.</para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">In C all types have a range or limits
            partially for efficiency reasons. The specification also says that a strictly conforming
            program will remain below the lowest limits. Now what these limits do is that increase
            the portability of program just like being the lowest common denominator.</para>
        </d:listitem>
        <d:listitem>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"><emphasis role="bold">object:</emphasis>
            region of data storage in the execution environment, the contents of which can represent
            values.When referenced, an object may be interpreted as having a particular type.</para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">These are what we know as variables in common
            developer language. The region of data storage occupied by an object will be contiguous
            number of bytes. Note that the term object used in ISO standard of C has nothing to do
            with object in object-oriented programming paradigm.</para>
        </d:listitem>
        <d:listitem>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"><emphasis role="bold">parameter:</emphasis>
            Also known as formal parameter or formal argument (deprecated). Object declared as part
            of a function declaration or definition that acquires a value on entry to the function,
            or an identifier from the comma-separated list bounded by the parentheses immediately
            following the macro name in a function-like macro definition.</para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">For example:</para>
          <d:programlisting role="CLexer">#define FUNC(X, Y) //two parameters

int f(int x);  //one parameter
void y(int y, int z); //two parameters</d:programlisting>
        </d:listitem>
        <d:listitem>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"><emphasis role="bold"> recommended
              practice:</emphasis> Specification that is strongly recommended as being in keeping
            with the intent of the standard, but that may be impractical for some
            implementations.</para>
        </d:listitem>
        <d:listitem>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"><emphasis role="bold">value:</emphasis>
            Precise meaning of the contents of an object when interpreted as having a specific
            type.</para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">This at times will depend on the type of
            machine. For example, a union containing an integer and two characters will have
            different values for characters on big-endian and little-endian machines. But on the
            same machine the meaning must be accurate for contents of an object.</para>
        </d:listitem>
        <d:listitem>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"><emphasis role="bold">implementation-defined
              value:</emphasis> Unspecified value where each implementation documents how the choice
            is made.</para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">There are certain values defined by the
            implementation. For example, in the table for defining numerical limits in chapter 3
            specification defines <code>INT_MAX</code> in a fashion as if integers are 16-bit. But
            all modern 32-bit compilers do not follow this limit and they treat integer as 32-bit
            entity. indeterminate value: Either an unspecified value or a trap
            representation.</para>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">Consider a variable declaration int i;. What
            value does this integer i contain? We do not know. The value contained is unspecified as
            per specification nomenclature. Developers also know this as garbage value. Behavior
            caused by usage of such variables will be known as unspecified behavior. However,
            behavior caused by a trap representation will be undefined behavior.</para>
        </d:listitem>
        <d:listitem>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"><emphasis role="bold">unspecified
              value:</emphasis> Valid value of the relevant type where International Standard
            imposes no requirements on which value is chosen in any instance. NOTE: An unspecified
            value cannot be a trap representation. As we have seen in last example the value of the
            variable will be unspecified value. </para>
        </d:listitem>
        <d:listitem>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"><inlineequation>
              <mml:math>
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mo>⌈</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mtext> x</mml:mtext>
                  <mml:mo>⌉</mml:mo>
                </mml:mrow>
              </mml:math>
            </inlineequation> : ceiling of x: the least integer greater than or equal to x.</para>
        </d:listitem>
        <d:listitem>
          <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"><inlineequation>
              <mml:math>
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mo>⌊</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mtext> x </mml:mtext>
                  <mml:mo>⌋</mml:mo>
                </mml:mrow>
              </mml:math>
            </inlineequation> : floor of x: the greatest integer less than or equal to x.</para>
        </d:listitem>
      </d:orderedlist>
      <d:para>You can also read the conformance part of this chapter which is chapter 3 in
        specification.</d:para>
    </d:sect1>
</d:chapter>
