<d:chapter version="5.0" xmlns:d="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <?xml-stylesheet href="../css/style.css" type="text/css"?>
    <?dbhtml filename="introduction/index.html" ?>
    <d:title> Introduction </d:title>
    <d:para>So it begins. The journey to a destination which will never be reached. The journey to
      perfection! The journey to perfect programs. I have read somewhere that a perfect program is
      one from which nothing can be deleted. Well, the fun is not in the destination but in journey.
      The process of learning is fun. And I will share this fun with you. Of all popular mainstream
      languages C, and Lisp are two oldest but we cannot really say that Lisp is really popular. It
      has a niche area and it is there for that. So let me redefine my statement. Of all
      general-purpose popular programming language C is the oldest. So what makes C so special that
      it is still out there. Well, C and Unix were born almost together in early 1970s. Then Unix
      was ported in C and the notion that operating systems can be only written in assembly
      language, because it has to do time critical things, was destroyed. After that Unix became
      very popular. Then when C++ was not yet there Windows was written in C and more and more
      programs were written in C. It might have been the case that Microsoft and Apple would have
      written their OS in C++ had it been there. So, essentially what happened that there is a lot
      of code base which is there in C. Also, C++’s backward compatibility is one of the reasons why
      C++ is so popular. When C was invented there was no structured programming language and code
      was mostly written in assembly. With C it gave the power of assembly and benefits of
      structured language like code reuse, modularity, and portability among others. Because of
      these reasons C became immensely popular and is still popular.</d:para>
    <d:para>C is simple, small, succinct. It may be dirty but is quick. It may have its quirks but
      it is a success. C is really so simple yet so deceptive. It will take one years of programming
      to really thoroughly understand it. Note that this book will make heavy use of C99
      specification. It will contain almost a copy of n1124.pdf which I have. </d:para>
    <d:section>
      <d:title>Organization</d:title>
      <d:para>I have will classify chapters in two categories. One is metalanguage specific and
        second specification specific. Chapter no. 2, 3 and 4 are very tightly related to
        specification while rest of the book is related to compiler and programming. Chapters which
        treat standard library of C include information from both specification and compiler. It is
        suggested that the reader reads chapter 2, 3 and 4 after finishing rest of the
        book.</d:para>
    </d:section>
    <d:section>
      <d:title>Why C?</d:title>
      <d:para>Because it is the most common denominator. Any language be it C++, Java, Perl, Python
        etc have got bindings in C. Whenever you are willing to extend these languages you need to
        know C. Also, if by any chance you are going towards system programming you need to C. C is
        everywhere. There is no escape from learning it; it does not matter whether you like it or
        not.</d:para>
      <d:para>There is one more important point worth noting here is that C++ is far more complex
        compared to C. Also, the runtime calculations of C++ make it slightly slower than C. The
        library of C is much smaller than C. Therefore wherever there is a memory constraint or
        extreme high performance is needed C is preferred. The simple syntax of C means its code is
        very verbose for programmer in the sense that if you read code then you can very easily see
        what instructions the code is going to translate into.</d:para>
      <d:para>It is very easy to write interfaces to other languages because other languages expose
        there objects in terms of C structures not the other way around. The reason for this is huge
        popularity of C, maturity and large code base.</d:para>
      <d:para>One more important feature is portability. Note that if you want your program to have
        high degree of portability then you should not use C99 features but rather ANSI C because
        ANSI C compilers are available on most platforms. Even though Java claims to be portable or
        other interpreted languages they are limited by the fact that the interpreters or VMs(JVM in
        case of Java) is not available on all the platforms. Therefore, C is the MOST portable
        language. :-)</d:para>
    </d:section>
    <d:section>
      <d:title>History</d:title>
      <d:para><d:indexterm>
          <d:primary>history</d:primary>
        </d:indexterm>
        <d:indexterm>
          <d:primary>Dennis</d:primary>
          <d:secondary>Ritchie</d:secondary>
        </d:indexterm> C was formally delivered to this world in 1972 and conceived by Dennis
        MacAlistair Ritchie in 1968. What happened was there was a project for development of a text
        processor and GE-645 was bought by AT&amp;T Bell Labs. At that time Ken Thompson had
        developed a game called “Space Travel”. Then they had another machine PDP-11. Before that
        they had PDP-7. Now all the time the code for “Space Travel” had to be rewritten and also
        the Unix had to be ported. So when C was invented it was used to write Unix code in C. And
        then “Space Travel”. I do not know what was the real motivation the language, the OS or the
        game. But such is the story. Also, I have not studied much in this area about the exact
        events. In 1972 C was formally announced. C takes its features from BCPL a language by
        Martin Richard and B by Ken Thompson. AT&amp;T Bells labs gave Unix and a C compiler to many
        universities at a normal fees and it grew with leaps and bounds from there and became a
        ubiquitous language. For many years “The C Programming Language” served as a reference of C.
        Later it was standardized by ANSI and then by ISO standards.</d:para>
    </d:section>
    <d:section>
      <title xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">Comparison with other Languages</title>
      <d:para>C is a structured, statically typed, somewhat low-level, high-performance compiled
        language. It does not support object-oriented programming like most modern programming
        including C++, Java, Perl, Python, Ruby etc. However, that does not mean you cannot do
        object-oriented programming in C. It is just that C does not have support at the language
        level and it is painful to do so. C is low level because it allows you to handle memory
        contents directly. You have something called void which is raw representation of memory
        content. C also does not support functional or generic programming but again it is possible
        to do so with painful hacks. One of the coveted features is C programs deliver very high
        performance if written correctly as it does not have reunite penalties of virtual functions
        of OOP (object-oriented programming) languages.</d:para>
    </d:section>
    <d:section>
      <title xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">How to Learn Programming?</title>
      <d:para>Programming is exactly like Mathematics. As in Mathematics you need to read theory,
        understand solved problems and then solve more and more problems by yourself. If you cannot
        solve ask your teacher. Similarly, in programming you need to read about language, try
        examples given, read code written by others and then develop your own code. If you get stuck
        there are umpteen number of tutorials, mailing lists and groups to help you. I recommend
        comp.lang.c user group for C programming. Its interface is at <d:link
          xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
          xlink:href="http://groups.google.com/group/comp.lang.c/"
          >http://groups.google.com/group/comp.lang.c/</d:link>. You should join it and participate
        there. <link xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
          xlink:href="http://www.stackoverflow.com/">http://www.stackoverflow.com/</link> is also a
        very good forum to ask questions about programming in general.</d:para>
    </d:section>
    <d:section>
      <title xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">What is a Computer Program?</title>
      <d:para>Since this book is written for even beginner please allow me to start from beginning.
        As the reader may know a computer consists of many components and one of the most or rather
        most important part is processor often named as CPU (central processing unit). The logic
        gates in CPUs are formed and instructions like ADD (addition), SUB (subtraction), MUL
        (multiplication), DIV (division) etc are implemented in hardware of CPU. When we write a
        program say C program the instructions given in our program is translated to a format which
        operating system can understand. In our case that is GNU/Linux this executable format is
        known as ELF (executable and linkable format). For the curious you can read <link
          xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
          xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Executable_and_Linkable_Format"
          >http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Executable_and_Linkable_Format</link> and there are lots of
        specification for different CPUs. Then operating system interprets these files and ask CPU
        to perform action. So a C program does not directly talk to processor but it rather talks to
        operating system or rather kernel of the operating system and in turn the operating system
        or kernel provides services to your program. There is a typical life cycle in development of
        a program. It has been given as a flowchart below.</d:para>
      <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
        <figure>
          <title>Development flowchart of a computer program.</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/flowchart.png" valign="middle" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </para>
    </d:section>
    <d:section>
      <title xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">Attributes of a Program</title>
      <d:para>You may be wondering so that is very easy. You just learn programming in C and start
        hacking on keyboard to produce software. Well, that is partially true but a program has
        several desired attributes which you must consider. Any program cannot be considered a good
        program unless it satisfies following requirements or possess following attributes (Note:
        These are generic attributes and not specific to C programming language):<orderedlist
          xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Correctness:</emphasis> Correctness means that a program
              satisfies its requirement specification. It means that for a specified input the
              specified output should be produced. This particular attribute is of most
              significance. It does not matter whether other attributes are present or not but this
              one is a must. If a program behavior is not correct then it is of no use.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Efficiency:</emphasis> Efficiency is second to correctness
              only. Say you are developing a text editor and you take 5 seconds to load a 10KB text
              file then by no means you can persuade a user to use you text editor. A programmable
              must be as efficient as possible. Sometimes it clashes with other attributes and also
              depend on the problem domain that how strict are the requirements.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Security:</emphasis> A very highly desirable feature in
              programs which deal with more than one computer and also for desktop applications. It
              is very bad if someone can take advantage of buffer overflow, stack overflow, integer
              overflow etc. in your program and you must guard against these at all times. Note that
              to provide security you must put extra checks which will go against efficiency.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Robustness:</emphasis> Sometimes users will not give correct
              inputs. For example they may enter a character when an integer is asked for or they
              can give input beyond range. In such cases you must handle the erroneous input. This
              is just one example. Sometimes your memory allocation may fail. The rule is program
              defensively. All such input validations and checks on memory do take a toll on our
              second attribute but that does not mean that we can neglect it.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Maintainability:</emphasis> Even a one line program has to
              be maintained if it is worth it! Typically the life of a program far exceeds the
              development time. In almost all the cases the original programmer is not maintainer.
              Because of these reasons you must strive for maintainability. You should follow some
              coding standards like I highly recommend <link
                xlink:href="http://www.gnu.org/prep/standards/">GNU Coding Stadards</link>. Clear
              documentation is one of the prerequisites of maintainability.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Extensibility:</emphasis> Let us take our example of text
              editor and say our editor is complete. Now someone else would like to provide a plugin
              which will enable syntax highlighting and project management for this editor. So, in
              order to do so you can choose a plugin-based extensible architecture or you can allow
              them to extend the editor using scripting languages like Guile, Python, Lua etc.This
              features allows user to collaborate and make your program better. Remember the rule is
              the more the merrier here.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Portability:</emphasis> It is an elusive and painful goal.
              Let us say we write our text editor GUI using something like Xlib directly then we
              will have to port the entire GUI for other non X-based OSes. So we can choose some
              cross-platform GUI libraries like GTK+, Qt, WxWidgets etc. Even then when system calls
              come in your software you can do not much but either write wrappers and do conditional
              compilation.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist></d:para>
    </d:section>
    <d:section>
      <title xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">Tools of Trade</title>
      <d:para>I am going to use Clang and gcc as compiler, Emacs as my editor with CEDET, ECB and
        Flymake. For debugging I will use xxgdb though you can debug in Emacs itself. I just love
        the good old X gui of xxgdb. For dynamic memory checking, heap corruption, cache corruption
        etc I am going to show you how to use valgrind. For profiling gprof and for code coverage
        gcov. Note that you can use gcc for compiling programs. Most of the systems come with gcc.
        However, I like clang for beginners because it is usually faster, produces better error
        messages (which is very important for a beginner) and typically consumes less memory. Also,
        it never hurts to know something new. For compiling programs I will use GNU Make though in
        the beginning I will show you how to compile on command line. Let us begin with Emacs
        configuration file <d:code>.emacs</d:code>:</d:para>
      <d:para>
        <d:programlisting role="CommonLispLexer" language="lisp">(custom-set-variables
;; custom-set-variables was added by Custom.
;; If you edit it by hand, you could mess it up, so be careful.
;; Your init file should contain only one such instance.
;; If there is more than one, they won't work right.
'(column-number-mode t)
'(cua-mode t nil (cua-base))
'(ecb-layout-name "leftright2")
'(ecb-options-version "2.40")
'(ecb-windows-height 0.2)
'(ecb-windows-width 0.2)
'(make-backup-files nil)
'(scroll-bar-mode (quote right)))
(custom-set-faces
;; custom-set-faces was added by Custom.
;; If you edit it by hand, you could mess it up, so be careful.
;; Your init file should contain only one such instance.
;; If there is more than one, they won't work right.
'(default ((t (:inherit nil :stipple nil :background "#ffffff" :foreground
"#221f1e" :inverse-video nil :box nil :strike-through nil :overline nil
:underline nil :slant normal :weight normal :height 98 :width
semi-condensed :foundry "misc" :family "fixed")))))
(require 'cedet)
(require 'semantic/analyze)
(provide 'semantic-analyze)
(provide 'semantic-ctxt)
(provide 'semanticdb)
(provide 'semanticdb-find)
(provide 'semanticdb-mode)
(provide 'semantic-load)
(load "~/.emacs.d/flymake.el")
(add-to-list 'load-path "~/.emacs.d/ecb-snap")

(require 'ecb)
(require 'ecb-autoloads)
(load "~/.emacs.d/rfringe.el")
(require 'rfringe)
(when (load "flymake" t)
(defun flymake-pylint-init ()
    (let* ((temp-file (flymake-init-create-temp-buffer-copy
    'flymake-create-temp-inplace))
    (local-file (file-relative-name
    temp-file
    (file-name-directory buffer-file-name))))
    (list "epylint" (list local-file))))

(add-to-list 'flymake-allowed-file-name-masks
    '("\.py\'" flymake-pylint-init)))
    (load-file "/usr/share/git-core/emacs/git.el")
    (".+\.c$" flymake-simple-make-init flymake-simple-cleanup
    flymake-get-real-file-name)
    (setq TeX-auto-save t)
    (setq TeX-parse-self t)
    (setq-default TeX-master nil)
    (load "auctex.el" nil t t)
    (load "preview-latex.el" nil t t)</d:programlisting>
      </d:para>
      <d:para>Just copy paste the following program in Emacs and the Makefile given after that:
        <d:programlisting role="CLexer">//Note:This listing will not compile. It has errors.
#include &lt;stdio.h

int main()
{
  return 0
}</d:programlisting></d:para>
      <d:caution>
        <d:title>Do not make a mistake here.</d:title>
        <d:para>
          <d:programlisting role="MakefileLexer">check-syntax:
  clang -o nul -Wall -S $(CHK_SOURCES)
</d:programlisting>
        </d:para>
      </d:caution>
      <d:para>Note that there should be a tab before the second line. If you do all steps correctly
        you should see something like: Note the pink background. If you move your mouse there then
        you will see the error/diagnostic messages from the compiler. For now I recommend you to
        read Emacs tutorial and man page of Clang compiler. I will introduce xxgdb and valgrind
        later. Note that you can modify Makefile but this particular content must remain unchanged.
        It is the enabler for Flymake. The screenshot is given below. Move your mouse over pink
        lines to see the error.</d:para>
      <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
        <figure>
          <title>Emacs Flymake Demo.</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/flymake.png" valign="middle" scale="100" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase/>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </para>
    </d:section>
    <d:section>
      <d:title>Bits and Bytes</d:title>
      <d:para>The smallest unit a computer can understand is called a bit. The values for a bit is
        either 0 or 1. Consider a voltage. It can be 0V or 1.5V or whatever the core CPU voltage is.
        CPU does not understand numbers but voltages :-). You cannot expect an electronics hardware
        to understand the same semantics of 0 and 1 which we know. 0 and 1 are abstraction of CPUs
        voltages in programming. Four bits form a nibble and eight form a byte. A byte is the area
        of memory which can be addressed by CPU and its content manipulated. To address a memory a
        CPU has say 4 or 8 or up to 256 pins. For example, in a common 32-bit CPU there are 32 pins
        whose voltages may represent 0 or 1. Consider all pins are low i.e. 0 then the memory
        location pointed to is 00000000000000000000000000000000 i.e. a 8 bit memory at location 0
        can be accessed. This memory is also called primary memory or RAM (Random Access Memory). So
        computing this way we can see that a 32-bit processor can access <d:inlineequation>
          <mml:math>
            <mml:mrow>
              <mml:msup>
                <mml:mi>2</mml:mi>
                <mml:mn>32</mml:mn>
              </mml:msup>
            </mml:mrow>
          </mml:math>
        </d:inlineequation> bytes or 4,294,967,296 bytes. You can arrive at this number by
        4*1024*1024*1024. This is equivalent to 4GB of RAM. However, modern Intel processors have 36
        physical pins to address up to 64GB of memory. </d:para>
      <d:para> Since a byte has 8 bits, its value may range from 0 to 255 as <d:inlineequation>
          <mml:math>
            <mml:mrow>
              <mml:msup>
                <mml:mi>2</mml:mi>
                <mml:mn>8</mml:mn>
              </mml:msup>
            </mml:mrow>
          </mml:math>
        </d:inlineequation> is 256. For unsigned data type this will be the range. When all bits are
        0 value is zero and when all are high it is 255. Computers use two's complement form to
        represent binary number. So if these 8-bits represent signed number the range will be from <d:inlineequation>
          <mml:math>
            <mml:mrow>
              <mml:mo>-</mml:mo>
              <mml:msup>
                <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
                <mml:mn>8</mml:mn>
              </mml:msup>
            </mml:mrow>
          </mml:math>
        </d:inlineequation> to <d:inlineequation>
          <mml:math>
            <mml:mrow>
              <mml:mo>-</mml:mo>
              <mml:msup>
                <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
                <mml:mn>8</mml:mn>
              </mml:msup>
              <mml:mtext> </mml:mtext>
              <mml:mo>-</mml:mo>
              <mml:mtext> 1</mml:mtext>
            </mml:mrow>
          </mml:math>
        </d:inlineequation> that is -128 to 127. As you will see later at lowest levels C allows you
        to access even one bit using something called bit-fields. You should read about two’s
        complement form at <d:link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Two’s_complement"> 2's
          Complement</d:link> in detail.</d:para>
    </d:section>
    <d:section>
      <d:title>Compiling and Executing</d:title>
      <d:para>To compile and execute a program create a new file, edit it and save it. The extension
        of file should be <d:code>*.c</d:code>. For example, <d:code>myprogram.c</d:code>. After
        that you can give this command at terminal. Here is the corrected code for
        you.<d:programlisting role="CLexer">#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

int main()
{
  return 0;
}</d:programlisting>
        Execute the following command on your command prompt:</d:para>
      <d:para><d:code>$</d:code><d:command>clang nothing.c -o nothing</d:command></d:para>
      <d:para>Then you will see a file named my program is created by compiler if no errors were
        there in your program. In case of errors, like we had in one shown to you they have to be
        resolved first. Suppose nothing is produced then you can execute it like</d:para>
      <d:para><d:code>$</d:code><d:command>./nothing</d:command></d:para>
      <d:para>Note that in both the commands $ is not part of command but it is prompt. For you it
        may be <d:code>%</d:code> or <d:code>#</d:code> or something fancier (depends on the
        imagination of your system administrator). To execute this command your working directory
        must be same as the directory your program is in. Also, note that on some systems TAB auto
        completes filename so do not do the following by accident:</d:para>
      <d:warning>
        <d:title>DO NOT DO THIS.</d:title>
        <d:para><d:code>$</d:code><d:command>clang nothing.c -o nothing.c</d:command></d:para>
      </d:warning>
      <d:para>This will overwrite your nothing.c by nothing. Let us see how to compile this program
        using a Makefile. Edit your Makefile like
        this:<d:programlisting role="MakefileLexer">#sample Makefile
check-syntax:
    clang -o nul -Wall -S $(CHK_SOURCES)

nothing:nothing.c
    clang nothing.c -o nothing</d:programlisting></d:para>
      <d:para>Now from do this from menu. From <d:guimenu>Tools</d:guimenu> select
          <d:guimenuitem>compile</d:guimenuitem>. As the command issue <d:command>make -k
          test</d:command>. Your code will be compiled. Makefiles are better than executing commands
        however you must know underlying commands. You can also use something like
          <d:application>CMake</d:application> or <d:application>Scons</d:application> but I think
        that should be part of a book covering build systems.</d:para>
    </d:section>
  </d:chapter>
