<d:preface version="5.0" xmlns:d="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <?xml-stylesheet href="../css/style.css" type="text/css"?>
    <?dbhtml filename="preface/index.html" ?>
      <d:title>Preface</d:title>
    <d:para> Welcome to this book on C programming using a particular specification version C99. As
      of now C99 is the latest specification fully implemented by C compilers. C11 is latest but it
      is yet to be implemented by compiler authors. I have been writing this book for a long time
      but it has yet to reach completion. Very soon a C11 version will be written as compilers start
      supporting C11 specification. These days I have noticed a tendency that people think Java, PHP
      or Python are more used and they have a tendency to overlook the merits of C as a programming
      language. The benefits of learning C is described further in Chapter 1 "Introduction". </d:para>
    <d:para> C is one of the language which is closest to system and very useful for system
      programming though not limited to it. It is also very fundamental to many languages as you
      will discover along your programming endeavours. I highly recommend that all programmers must
      learn C programmer in order to become a better programmer. You do not have many choices in the
      category of compiled languages anyway.
    </d:para>
    <d:para>
      For topics not covered in the book have a look at compiler support for
      gcc <d:link xlink:href="https://gcc.gnu.org/wiki/C11Status">gcc's c11
      status page</d:link>. As soon as features will be available in gcc I will
      update the book. This is one of the reasons I am not giving pdf because
      the book is subject to change and I keep adding material. However, the
      docbook source can be downloaded from <d:link
      xlink:href="https://github.com/shivshankardayal/C99-Programming-Docbook">github
      repository</d:link> and a pdf copy can be produced using
      <d:code>dblatex</d:code>. Do not try to Apache FOP because it messes up
      tables and some potion will need to be changed for tables before you can
      process it with Apache FOP.
    </d:para>
    <d:section>
      <d:title>Acknowledgements</d:title>
      <d:para>I do not have much to write in preface as I have covered most of it in Chapter 1.
        Therefore, I will skip directly to acknowledgements section. First, I would like to thank my
        parents, wife and son for taking out their fair share of time and the support which they
        have extended to me during my bad times. After that I would like to pay my most sincere
        gratitude to my teachers particularly H. N. Singh, Yogendra Yadav, Satyanand Satyarthi,
        Kumar Shailesh and Prof. T. K. Basu. Now is the turn of people from software community. I
        must thank the entire free software community for all the resources they have developed to
        make computing better. However, few names I know and here they go. Richard Stallman is the
        first, Donald Knuth, Dennis Ritchie, Ken Thompson, Bjarne Stroustrup after that. I possibly
        cannot write all the names because then possibly an entire chapter will be full of those
        names. :-) I am using Docbook to write this book therefore obviously Normal Walsh deserves
        praise for his work on it. </d:para>
      <d:para>I am not a native English speaker and this book has just gone through one pair of eyes
        therefore chances are high that it will have lots of errors. At the same time it may contain
        lots of technical errors. Please feel free to drop me an email at
          <d:email>shivshankar.dayal@gmail.com</d:email>. I will try to fix all errors and
        incorporate your valuable suggestions. </d:para>
    </d:section>
  </d:preface>
