<d:chapter version="5.0" xmlns:d="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <?xml-stylesheet href="../css/style.css" type="text/css"?>
    <?dbhtml filename="std/index.html" ?>
    <d:title>The C Standard Library</d:title>
    <d:para>This chapter and rest of book eflects chapter 7 of
    n1124.pdf. This chapter begins with assert.h. We will see three
    parts of each function/macro as much as possible. From
    specification, compiler and example point of view in that
    order.</d:para>
    <d:sect1>
      <d:title>Introduction</d:title>
      <d:sect2>
	<d:title>Definition of Terms</d:title>
	<d:para>A <d:emphasis role="italic">string</d:emphasis> is a contiguous
	sequence of characters terminated by and including the first null
	character. The term <d:emphasis role="italic">multibyte
	string</d:emphasis> is sometimes used instead to emphasize special
	processing given to multibyte characters contained in the string or to
	avoid confusion with a <d:emphasis role="italic">wide
	string</d:emphasis>. A <d:emphasis role="italic">pointer to a
	string</d:emphasis> is a pointer to its initial (lowest addressed)
	character. The length of a string is the number of bytes preceding the
	null character and the <d:emphasis role="italic">value of a
	string</d:emphasis> is the sequence of the values of the contained
	characters, in order.</d:para>
	<d:para>The <d:emphasis role="italic">decimal-point
	character</d:emphasis> is the character used by functions that convert
	floating-point numbers to or from character sequences to denote the
	beginning of the fractional part of such character
	sequences.<d:footnote><d:para>The functions that make use of the
	decimal-point character are the numeric conversion functions (14.20.1,
	14.24.4.1) and the formatted input/output functions (14.19.6,
	14.24.2).</d:para></d:footnote>  It is represented in the text and
	examples by a period, but may be changed by the
	<d:code>setlocale</d:code> function.</d:para>
	<d:para>A <d:emphasis role="italic">null wide character</d:emphasis> is
	a wide character with code value zero.</d:para>
	<d:para>A <d:emphasis role="italic">wide string</d:emphasis> is a
	contiguous sequence of wide characters terminated by and including the
	first null wide character. A <d:emphasis role="italic">pointer to a
	wide string</d:emphasis> is a pointer to its initial (lowest addressed)
	wide character. The <d:emphasis role="italic">length of a wide
	string</d:emphasis> is the number of wide characters preceding the null
	wide character and the <d:emphasis role="italic">value of a wide
	string</d:emphasis> is the sequence of code values of the contained
	wide characters, in order.</d:para>
	<d:para>A <d:emphasis role="italic">shift sequence</d:emphasis> is a
	contiguous sequence of bytes within a multibyte string that
	(potentially) causes a change in shift state. A shift sequence shall
	not have a corresponding wide character; it is instead taken to be an
	adjunct to an adjacent multibyte character.<d:footnote><d:para>For
	state-dependent encodings, the values for <d:code>MB_CUR_MAX</d:code>
	and <d:code>MB_LEN_MAX</d:code> shall thus be large enough to count all
	the bytes in any complete multibyte character plus at least one
	adjacent shift sequence of maximum length. Whether these counts provide
	for more than one shift sequence is the implementation’s
	choice.</d:para></d:footnote></d:para>
      </d:sect2>
      <d:sect2>
	<d:title>Standard Headers</d:title>
	<d:para>Each library function is declared, with a type that includes a
	prototype, in a header,<d:footnote><d:para>A header is not necessarily
	a source file, nor are the &lt; and > delimited sequences in header
	names necessarily valid source file names.</d:para></d:footnote>
	whose contents are made available by the <d:code>#include</d:code>
	preprocessing directive. The header declares a set of related
	functions, plus any necessary types and additional macros needed to
	facilitate their use. Declarations of types described in this clause
	shall not include type qualifiers, unless explicitly stated
	otherwise.</d:para>
	<d:para>The standard headers are:</d:para>
	<d:screen>&amp;lt;assert.h>  &amp;lt;inttypes.h> &amp;lt;signal.h>  &amp;lt;stdlib.h>
&amp;lt;complex.h> &amp;lt;iso646.h>   &amp;lt;stdarg.h>  &amp;lt;string.h>
&amp;lt;ctype.h>   &amp;lt;limits.h>   &amp;lt;stdbool.h> &amp;lt;tgmath.h>
&amp;lt;errno.h>   &amp;lt;locale.h>   &amp;lt;stddef.h>  &amp;lt;time.h>
&amp;lt;fenv.h>    &amp;lt;math.h>     &amp;lt;stdint.h>  &amp;lt;wchar.h>
&amp;lt;float.h>   &amp;lt;setjmp.h>   &amp;lt;stdio.h>   &amp;lt;wctype.h></d:screen>
<d:para>If a file with the same name as one of the above &amp;lt; and >
delimited sequences, not provided as part of the implementation, is placed in
any of the standard places that are searched for included source files, the
behavior is undefined.</d:para>

<d:para>Standard headers may be included in any order; each may be included
more thanonce in a giv en scope, with no effect different from being included
only once, except that the effect of including
<d:code>&amp;lt;assert.h></d:code> depends on the definition of
<d:code>NDEBUG</d:code> (see 14.2). If used, a header shall be included outside
of any external declaration or definition, and it shall first be included
before the first reference to any of the functions or objects it declares, or
to any of the types or macros it defines. However, if an identifier is declared
or defined in more than one header, the second and subsequent associated
headers may be included after the initial reference to the identifier. The
program shall not have any macros with names lexically identical to keywords
currently defined prior to the inclusion.</d:para>
<d:para>Any definition of an object-like macro described in this clause shall
expand to code that is fully protected by parentheses where necessary, so that
it groups in an arbitrary expression as if it were a single
identifier.</d:para>
<d:para>Any declaration of a library function shall have external
linkage.</d:para>
<d:para>A summary of the contents of the standard headers is given in annex
B.</d:para>
<d:para><d:para>Forward references:</d:para> diagnostics (14.2).</d:para>
      </d:sect2>
      <d:sect2>
	<d:title>Reserved Identifiers</d:title>
	<d:para>Each header declares or defines all identifiers listed in its
	associated subclause, and optionally declares or defines identifiers
	listed in its associated future library directions subclause and
	identifiers which are always reserved either for any use or for use as
	file scope identifiers.</d:para>
	<d:itemizedlist>
	  <d:listitem>
	    <d:para>All identifiers that begin with an underscore and either an
	    uppercase letter or another underscore are always reserved for any
	    use.</d:para>
	  </d:listitem>
	  <d:listitem>
	    <d:para>All identifiers that begin with an underscore are always
	    reserved for use as identifiers with file scope in both the
	    ordinary and tag name spaces.</d:para>
	  </d:listitem>
	  <d:listitem>
	    <d:para>Each macro name in any of the following subclauses
	    (including the future library directions) is reserved for use as
	    specified if any of its associated headers is included; unless
	    explicitly stated otherwise (see 14.1.4).</d:para>
	  </d:listitem>
	  <d:listitem>
	    <d:para>All identifiers with external linkage in any of the
	    following subclauses (including the future library directions) are
	    always reserved for use as identifiers with external
	    linkage.<d:footnote><d:para>The list of reserved identifiers with
	    external linkage includes <d:code>errno, ath_errhandling,
	    setjmp,</d:code> and
	    <d:code>va_end</d:code>.</d:para></d:footnote></d:para>
	  </d:listitem>
	  <d:listitem>
	    <d:para>Each identifier with file scope listed in any of the
	    following subclauses (including the future library directions) is
	    reserved for use as a macro name and as an identifier with file
	    scope in the same name space if any of its associated headers is
	    included.</d:para>
	  </d:listitem>
	</d:itemizedlist>
	<d:para>No other identifiers are reserved. If the program declares or
	defines an identifier in a context in which it is reserved (other than
	as allowed by 14.1.4), or defines a reserved identifier as a macro
	name, the behavior is undefined.</d:para>
	<d:para>If the program removes (with <d:code>#undef</d:code>) any macro
	definition of an identifier in the first group listed above, the
	behavior is undefined.</d:para>
      </d:sect2>
      <d:sect2>
	<d:title>Use of Library Functions</d:title>
	<d:para>Each of the following statements applies unless explicitly
	stated otherwise in the detailed descriptions that follow: If an
	argument to a function has an invalid value (such as a value outside
	the domain of the function, or a pointer outside the address space of
	the program, or a null pointer, or a pointer to non-modifiable storage
	when the corresponding parameter is not const-qualified) or a type
	(after promotion) not expected by a function with variable number of
	arguments, the behavior is undefined. If a function argument is
	described as being an array, the pointer actually passed to the
	function shall have a value such that all address computations and
	accesses to objects (that would be valid if the pointer did point to
	the first element of such an array) are in fact valid. Any function
	declared in a header may be additionally implemented as a function-like
	macro defined in the header, so if a library function is declared
	explicitly when its header is included, one of the techniques shown
	below can be used to ensure the declaration is not affected by such a
	macro. Any macro definition of a function can be suppressed locally by
	enclosing the name of the function in parentheses, because the name is
	then not followed by the left parenthesis that indicates expansion of a
	macro function name. For the same syntactic reason, it is permitted to
	take the address of a library function even if it is also defined as a
	macro.<d:footnote><d:para>This means that an implementation shall
	provide an actual function for each library function, even if it also
	provides a macro for that function.</d:para></d:footnote> The use of
	<d:code>#undef</d:code> to remove any macro definition will also ensure
	that an actual function is referred to. Any invocation of a library
	function that is implemented as a macro shall expand to code that
	evaluates each of its arguments exactly once, fully protected by
	parentheses where necessary, so it is generally safe to use arbitrary
	expressions as arguments. Likewise, those function-like macros
	described in the following subclauses may be invoked in an expression
	anywhere a function with a compatible return type could be
	called.<d:footnote><d:para>Such macros might not contain the sequence
	points that the corresponding function calls do.</d:para></d:footnote>
	All object-like macros listed as expanding to integer constant
	expressions shall additionally be suitable for use in
	<d:code>#if</d:code> preprocessing directives.</d:para>
	<d:para>Provided that a library function can be declared without
	reference to any type defined in a header, it is also permissible to
	declare the function and use it without including its associated
	header.</d:para>
	<d:para>There is a sequence point immediately before a library function
	returns.</d:para>
	<d:para>The functions in the standard library are not guaranteed to be
	reentrant and may modify objects with static storage
	duration.<d:footnote><d:para>Thus, a signal handler cannot, in general,
	call standard library functions.</d:para></d:footnote></d:para>
      </d:sect2>
    </d:sect1>
</d:chapter>
