<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<d:chapter version="5.0" xmlns:d="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <?dbhtml filename="stdlib/index.html" ?>
  <d:title>General utilities &lt;stdlib.h&gt;</d:title>
  <d:para>
    The header <d:code>&lt;stdlib.h&gt;</d:code> declares five types and
    several functions of general utility, and defines several macros.
  </d:para>
  <d:para>
    The types declared are <d:code>size_t</d:code> and <d:code>wchar_t</d:code>
    (both described in &#xa7; iso.7.19),
  </d:para>
  <d:blockquote>
    <d:para><d:code>div_t</d:code></d:para>
  </d:blockquote>
  <d:para>
    which is a structure type that is the type of the value returned by the
    <d:code>div</d:code> function,
  </d:para>
  <d:blockquote>
    <d:para><d:code>ldiv_t</d:code></d:para>
  </d:blockquote>
  <d:para>
    which is a structure type that is the type of the value returned by the
    <d:code>ldiv</d:code> function, and
  </d:para>
  <d:blockquote>
    <d:para><d:code>lldiv_t</d:code></d:para>
  </d:blockquote>
  <d:para>
    which is a structure type that is the type of the value returned by the
    <d:code>lldiv</d:code> function.
  </d:para>
  <d:para>
    The macros defined are <d:code>NULL</d:code> (described in &#xa7;
    iso.7.19);
  </d:para>
  <d:blockquote>
    <d:para><d:code>EXIT_FAILURE</d:code></d:para>
  </d:blockquote>
  <d:para>and</d:para>
  <d:blockquote>
    <d:para><d:code>EXIT_SUCCESS</d:code></d:para>
  </d:blockquote>
  <d:para>
    which expand to integer constant expressions that can be used as the
    argument to the <d:code>exit</d:code> function to return unsuccessful or
    successful termination status, respectively, to the host environment;
  </d:para>
  <d:blockquote>
    <d:para><d:code>RAND_MAX</d:code></d:para>
  </d:blockquote>
  <d:para>
    which expands to an integer constant expression that is the maximum
    value returned by the <d:code>rand</d:code> function; and
  </d:para>
  <d:blockquote>
    <d:para><d:code>MB_CUR_MAX</d:code></d:para>
  </d:blockquote>
  <d:para>
    which expands to a positive integer expression with type
    <d:code>size_t</d:code> that is the maximum number of bytes in a multibyte
    character for the extended character set specified by the current locale
    (category <d:code>LC_CTYPE</d:code>), which is never greater than
    <d:code>MB_LEN_MAX</d:code>.
  </d:para>
  <d:sect1 id="num_conv_func">
    <d:title>Numeric conversion functions</d:title>
    <d:para>
      The functions <d:code>atof, atoi, atol</d:code> and
      <d:code>atoll</d:code> need not affect the value of the integer
      expression <d:code>errno</d:code> on an error. If the value of the result
      cannot be represented, the behavior is undefined.
    </d:para>
    <d:sect2>
      <d:title>The atof function</d:title>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Synopsis</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:programlisting role="CLexer"><![CDATA[#include <stdlib.h>
double atof(const char *nptr);]]>
      </d:programlisting>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Description</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>atof</d:code> function converts the initial portion
        of the string pointed to by <d:code>nptr</d:code> to
        <d:code>double</d:code> representation. Except for the behavior on
        error, it is equivalent to
        <d:blockquote>
          <d:para><d:code>strtod(nptr, (char **)NULL)</d:code></d:para>
        </d:blockquote>
      </d:para>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Returns</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>atof</d:code> function returns the converted value.
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        <d:emphasis role="bold">Forward references:</d:emphasis> <d:xref
        linkend="str_to_decimal" />.
      </d:para>
    </d:sect2>
    <d:sect2>
      <d:title>The atoi, atol and atoll functions</d:title>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Synopsis</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:programlisting role="CLexer"><![CDATA[#include <stdlib.h>
int atoi(const char *nptr);
long int atol(const char *nptr);
long long int atoll(const char *nptr);]]>
      </d:programlisting>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Description</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>atoi, atol</d:code> and <d:code>atoll</d:code> functions
        convert the initial portion of the string pointed to by
        <d:code>nptr</d:code> to <d:code>int, long int</d:code> and
        <d:code>long long int</d:code> representation, respectively. Except for
        the behavior on error, they are equivalent to
        <d:blockquote>
          <d:para><d:code>atoi:  (int)strtol(nptr, (char **)NULL,
          10)</d:code></d:para>
          <d:para><d:code>atol:  strtol(nptr, (char **)NULL,
          10)</d:code></d:para>
          <d:para><d:code>atoll: strtoll(nptr, (char **)NULL,
          10)</d:code></d:para>
        </d:blockquote>
      </d:para>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Returns</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>atoi, atol</d:code> and <d:code>atoll</d:code> functions
        return the converted value.
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        <d:emphasis role="bold">Forward references:</d:emphasis> <d:xref
        linkend="str_to_long" />.
      </d:para>
    </d:sect2>
    <d:sect2 id="str_to_decimal">
      <d:title>The strtod, strtof and strtold functions</d:title>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Synopsis</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:programlisting role="CLexer"><![CDATA[#include <stdlib.h>
double strtod(const char * restrict nptr,
              char ** restrict endptr);
float strtof(const char * restrict nptr,
             char ** restrict endptr);
long double strtold(const char * restrict nptr,
                    char ** restrict endptr);]]>
      </d:programlisting>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Description</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>strtod, strtof</d:code> and <d:code>strtold</d:code>
        functions convert the initial portion of the string pointed to by
        <d:code>nptr</d:code> to <d:code>double, float</d:code> and
        <d:code>long double</d:code> representation, respectively. First, they
        decompose the input string into three parts: an initial, possibly
        empty, sequence of white-space characters (as specified by the
        <d:code>isspace</d:code> function), a subject sequence resembling a
        floating-point constant or representing an infinity or NaN; and a final
        string of one or more unrecognized characters, including the
        terminating null character of the input string. Then, they attempt to
        convert the subject sequence to a floating-point number, and return the
        result.
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        The expected form of the subject sequence is an optional plus or minus sign, then one of
        the following:
        <d:itemizedlist>
          <d:listitem>
            a nonempty sequence of decimal digits optionally containing a
            decimal-point character, then an optional exponent part as defined
            in (&#xa7; iso.6.4.4.2);
          </d:listitem>
          <d:listitem>
            a <d:code>0x</d:code> or <d:code>0X</d:code>, then a nonempty
            sequence of hexadecimal digits optionally containing a
            decimal-point character, then an optional binary exponent part as
            defined in (&#xa7; iso.6.4.4.2);
          </d:listitem>
          <d:listitem>
            <d:code>INF</d:code> or <d:code>INFINITY</d:code>, ignoring case
          </d:listitem>
          <d:listitem>
            <d:code>NAN</d:code> or <d:code>NAN</d:code> (<d:emphasis
            role="italic">n-char-sequence<d:subscript>opt</d:subscript></d:emphasis>),
            ignoring case in the <d:code>NAN</d:code> part, where:
            <d:blockquote>
              <d:para>
                <d:emphasis role="italic">n-char-sequence:</d:emphasis>
                <d:blockquote>
                  <d:para>
                    <d:emphasis role="italic">digit</d:emphasis>
                  </d:para>
                  <d:para>
                    <d:emphasis role="italic">nondigit</d:emphasis>
                  </d:para>
                  <d:para>
                    <d:emphasis role="italic">n-char-sequence digit</d:emphasis>
                  </d:para>
                  <d:para>
                    <d:emphasis role="italic">n-char-sequence
                    nondigit</d:emphasis>
                  </d:para>
                </d:blockquote>
              </d:para>
            </d:blockquote>
          </d:listitem>
        </d:itemizedlist>
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        The subject sequence is defined as the longest initial subsequence of
        the input string, starting with the first non-white-space character,
        that is of the expected form. The subject sequence contains no
        characters if the input string is not of the expected form.
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        If the subject sequence has the expected form for a floating-point
        number, the sequence of characters starting with the first digit or the
        decimal-point character (whichever occurs first) is interpreted as a
        floating constant according to the rules of (&#xa7; iso.6.4.4.2),
        except that the decimal-point character is used in place of a period,
        and that if neither an exponent part nor a decimal-point character
        appears in a decimal floating point number, or if a binary exponent
        part does not appear in a hexadecimal floating point number, an
        exponent part of the appropriate type with value zero is assumed to
        follow the last digit in the string. If the subject sequence begins
        with a minus sign, the sequence is interpreted as
        negated.<d:footnote><d:para>It is unspecified whether a minus-signed
        sequence is converted to a negative number directly or by negating the
        value resulting from converting the corresponding unsigned sequence
        (see &#xa7; iso.F.5); the two methods may yield different results if
        rounding is toward positive or negative infinity. In either case, the
        functions honor the sign of zero if floating-point arithmetic supports
        signed zeros.</d:para></d:footnote> A character sequence
        <d:code>INF</d:code> or <d:code>INFINITY</d:code> is interpreted as an
        infinity, if representable in the return type, else like a floating
        constant that is too large for the range of the return type. A
        character sequence <d:code>NAN</d:code> or <d:code>NAN</d:code>
        (<d:emphasis
        role="italic">n-char-sequence<d:subscript>opt</d:subscript></d:emphasis>)
        is interpreted as a quiet NaN, if supported in the return type, else
        like a subject sequence part that does not have the expected form; the
        meaning of the n-char sequence is
        implementation-defined.<d:footnote><d:para>An implementation may use
        the n-char sequence to determine extra information to be represented in
        the NaN's significand.</d:para></d:footnote> A pointer to the final
        string is stored in the object pointed to by <d:code>endptr</d:code>,
        provided that <d:code>endptr</d:code> is not a null pointer.
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        If the subject sequence has the hexadecimal form and
        <d:code>FLT_RADIX</d:code> is a power of 2, the value resulting from
        the conversion is correctly rounded.
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        In other than the <d:code>"C"</d:code> locale, additional
        locale-specific subject sequence forms may be accepted.
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        If the subject sequence is empty or does not have the expected form, no
        conversion is performed; the value of <d:code>nptr</d:code> is stored
        in the object pointed to by <d:code>endptr</d:code>, provided that
        <d:code>endptr</d:code> is not a null pointer.
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        <d:emphasis role="bold">Recommended practice</d:emphasis>
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        If the subject sequence has the hexadecimal form,
        <d:code>FLT_RADIX</d:code> is not a power of 2, and the result is not
        exactly representable, the result should be one of the two numbers in
        the appropriate internal format that are adjacent to the hexadecimal
        floating source value, with the extra stipulation that the error should
        have a correct sign for the current rounding direction.
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        If the subject sequence has the decimal form and at most
        <d:code>DECIMAL_DIG</d:code> (defined in
        <d:code>&lt;float.h&gt;</d:code>) significant digits, the result should
        be correctly rounded. If the subject sequence <d:emphasis
        role="italic">D</d:emphasis> has the decimal form and more than
        <d:code>DECIMAL_DIG</d:code> significant digits, consider the two
        bounding, adjacent decimal strings <d:emphasis
        role="italic">L</d:emphasis> and <d:emphasis
        role="italic">U</d:emphasis>, both having <d:code>DECIMAL_DIG</d:code>
        significant digits, such that the values of <d:emphasis
        role="italic">L, D</d:emphasis> and <d:emphasis
        role="italic">U</d:emphasis> satisfy <d:emphasis
        role="italic">L</d:emphasis>
        <d:inlineequation>
          <math
              xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mo>&#8804;</mo></math>
          </d:inlineequation> <d:emphasis role="italic">D</d:emphasis>
          <d:inlineequation>
          <math
              xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mo>&#8804;</mo></math>
      </d:inlineequation> <d:emphasis role="italic">U</d:emphasis>. The result
      should be one of the (equal or adjacent) values that would be obtained by
      correctly rounding <d:emphasis role="italic">L</d:emphasis> and
      <d:emphasis role="italic">U</d:emphasis> according to the current
      rounding direction, with the extra stipulation that the error with
      respect to <d:emphasis role="italic">D</d:emphasis> should have a correct
      sign for the current rounding
      direction.<d:footnote><d:para><d:code>DECIMAL_DIG</d:code>, defined in
      <d:code>&lt;float.h&gt;</d:code>, should be sufficiently large that
      <d:emphasis 
      role="italic">L</d:emphasis> and <d:emphasis role="italic">U</d:emphasis>
      will usually round to the same internal floating value, but if not will
      round to adjacent values.</d:para></d:footnote>
      </d:para>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Returns</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The functions return the converted value, if any. If no conversion
        could be performed, zero is returned. If the correct value overflows
        and default rounding is in effect (&#xa7; iso.7.12.1), plus or minus
        <d:code>HUGE_VAL, HUGE_VALF</d:code> or <d:code>HUGE_VALL</d:code> is
        returned (according to the return type and sign of the value), and the
        value of the macro <d:code>ERANGE</d:code> is stored in
        <d:code>errno</d:code>. If the result underflows (&#xa7; iso.7.12.1),
        the functions return a value whose magnitude is no greater than the
        smallest normalized positive number in the return type; whether
        <d:code>errno</d:code> acquires the value <d:code>ERANGE</d:code> is
        implementation-defined.
      </d:para>
    </d:sect2>
    <d:sect2 id="str_to_long">
      <d:title>The strtol, strtoll, strtoul and strtoull functions</d:title>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Synopsis</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:programlisting role="CLexer"><![CDATA[#include <stdlib.h> long int strtol(
    const char * restrict nptr,
    char ** restrict endptr,
    int base);
long long int strtoll(
    const char * restrict nptr,
    char ** restrict endptr,
    int base);
unsigned long int strtoul(
    const char * restrict nptr,
    char ** restrict endptr,
    int base);
unsigned long long int strtoull(
    const char * restrict nptr,
    char ** restrict endptr,
    int base);]]>
      </d:programlisting>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Description</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>strtol, strtoll, strtoul</d:code> and
        <d:code>strtoull</d:code> functions convert the initial portion of the
        string pointed to by <d:code>nptr</d:code> to <d:code>long int, long
        long int, unsigned long int</d:code> and <d:code>unsigned long long
        int</d:code> representation, respectively. First, they decompose the
        input string into three parts: an initial, possibly empty, sequence of
        white-space characters (as specified by the <d:code>isspace</d:code>
        function), a subject sequence resembling an integer represented in some
        radix determined by the value of <d:code>base</d:code>, and a final
        string of one or more unrecognized characters, including the
        terminating null character of the input string. Then, they attempt to
        convert the subject sequence to an integer, and return the result.
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        If the value of <d:code>base</d:code> is zero, the expected form of the
        subject sequence is that of an integer constant as described in (&#xa7;
        iso.6.4.4.1), optionally preceded by a plus or minus sign, but not
        including an integer suffix. If the value of <d:code>base</d:code> is
        between 2 and 36 (inclusive), the expected form of the subject sequence
        is a sequence of letters and digits representing an integer with the
        radix specified by <d:code>base</d:code>, optionally preceded by a plus
        or minus sign, but not including an integer suffix. The letters from
        <d:code>a</d:code> (or <d:code>A</d:code>) through <d:code>z</d:code>
        (or <d:code>Z</d:code>) are ascribed the values 10 through 35; only
        letters and digits whose ascribed values are less than that of
        <d:code>base</d:code> are 
        permitted. If the value of <d:code>base</d:code> is 16, the characters
        <d:code>0x</d:code> or <d:code>0X</d:code> may optionally precede the
        sequence of letters and digits, following the sign if present.
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        The subject sequence is defined as the longest initial subsequence of
        the input string, starting with the first non-white-space character,
        that is of the expected form. The subject sequence contains no
        characters if the input string is empty or consists entirely of white
        space, or if the first non-white-space character is other than a sign
        or a permissible letter or digit.
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        If the subject sequence has the expected form and the value of
        <d:code>base</d:code> is zero, the sequence of characters starting with
        the first digit is interpreted as an integer constant according to the
        rules of (&#xa7; iso.6.4.4.1). If the subject sequence has the expected
        form and the value of <d:code>base</d:code> is between 2 and 36, it is
        used as the base for conversion, ascribing to each letter its value as
        given above. If the subject sequence begins with a minus sign, the
        value resulting from the conversion is negated (in the return type). A
        pointer to the final string is stored in the object pointed to by
        <d:code>endptr</d:code>, provided that <d:code>endptr</d:code> is not a
        null pointer.
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        In other than the <d:code>"C"</d:code> locale, additional
        locale-specific subject sequence forms may be accepted.
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        If the subject sequence is empty or does not have the expected form, no
        conversion is performed; the value of <d:code>nptr</d:code> is stored
        in the object pointed to by <d:code>endptr</d:code>, provided that
        <d:code>endptr</d:code> is not a null pointer.
      </d:para>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Returns</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>strtol, strtoll, strtoul</d:code> and
        <d:code>strtoull</d:code> functions return the converted value, if
        any. If no conversion could be performed, zero is returned. If the
        correct value is outside the range of representable values,
        <d:code>LONG_MIN, LONG_MAX, LLONG_MIN, LLONG_MAX, ULONG_MAX</d:code> or
        <d:code>ULLONG_MAX</d:code> is returned (according to the return type
        and sign of the value, if any), and the value of the macro
        <d:code>ERANGE</d:code> is stored in <d:code>errno</d:code>.
      </d:para>
    </d:sect2>
  </d:sect1>
  <d:sect1>
    <d:title>Pseudo-random sequence generation functions</d:title>
    <d:sect2>
      <d:title>The rand function</d:title>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Synopsis</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:programlisting role="CLexer"><![CDATA[#include <stdlib.h>
int rand(void);]]>
      </d:programlisting>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Description</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>rand</d:code> function computes a sequence of pseudo-random
        integers in the range 0 to
        <d:code>RAND_MAX</d:code>.<d:footnote><d:para>There are no guarantees
        as to the quality of the random sequence produced and some
        implementations are known to produce sequences with distressingly
        non-random low-order bits. Applications with particular requirements
        should use a generator that is known to be sufficient for their
        needs.</d:para></d:footnote>
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>rand</d:code> function is not required to avoid data races
        with other calls to pseudo-random sequence generation functions. The
        implementation shall behave as if no library function calls the
        <d:code>rand</d:code> function.
      </d:para>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Returns</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>rand</d:code> function returns a pseudo-random integer.
      </d:para>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Environmental
      limits</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>The value of the <d:code>RAND_MAX</d:code> macro shall be at
      least 32767.</d:para>
    </d:sect2>
    <d:sect2>
      <d:title>The srand function</d:title>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Synopsis</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:programlisting role="CLexer"><![CDATA[#include <stdlib.h>
void srand(unsigned int seed);]]>
      </d:programlisting>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Description</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>srand</d:code> function uses the argument as a seed for a
        new sequence of pseudo-random numbers to be returned by subsequent
        calls to <d:code>rand</d:code>. If <d:code>srand</d:code> is then
        called with the same seed value, the sequence of pseudo-random numbers
        shall be repeated. If <d:code>rand</d:code> is called before any calls
        to srand have been made, the same sequence shall be generated as when
        <d:code>srand</d:code> is first called with a seed value of 1.
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>srand</d:code> function is not required to avoid data races
        with other calls to pseudo- random sequence generation functions. The
        implementation shall behave as if no library function calls the
        <d:code>srand</d:code> function.
      </d:para>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Returns</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>srand</d:code> function returns no value.
      </d:para>
      <d:para role="example">
        EXAMPLE The following functions define a portable implementation of
        <d:code>rand</d:code> and <d:code>srand</d:code>.
      </d:para>
      <d:programlisting role="CLexer"><![CDATA[static unsigned long int next = 1;
int rand(void) // RAND_MAX assumed to be 32767 {
  next = next * 1103515245 + 12345;
  return (unsigned int)(next/65536) % 32768;
}
void srand(unsigned int seed)
{
  next = seed;
}]]>
      </d:programlisting>
    </d:sect2>
  </d:sect1>
  <d:sect1>
    <d:title>Memory management functions</d:title>
    <d:para>
      The order and contiguity of storage allocated by successive calls to
      the<d:code> aligned_alloc, calloc, malloc</d:code> and
      <d:code>realloc</d:code> functions is unspecified. The pointer returned
      if the allocation succeeds is suitably aligned so that it may be assigned
      to a pointer to any type of object with a fundamental alignment
      requirement and then used to access such an object or an array of such
      objects in the space allocated (until the space is explicitly
      deallocated). The lifetime of an allocated object extends from the
      allocation until the deallocation. Each such allocation shall yield a
      pointer to an object disjoint from any other object. The pointer returned
      points to the start (lowest byte address) of the allocated space. If the
      space cannot be allocated, a null pointer is returned. If the size of the
      space requested is zero, the behavior is implementation-defined: either a
      null pointer is returned, or the behavior is as if the size were some
      nonzero value, except that the returned pointer shall not be used to
      access an object.
    </d:para>
    <d:para>
      For purposes of determining the existence of a data race, memory
      allocation functions behave as though they accessed only memory locations
      accessible through their arguments and not other static duration
      storage. These functions may, however, visibly modify the storage that
      they allocate or deallocate. A call to <d:code>free</d:code> or
      <d:code>realloc</d:code> that deallocates a region p of memory
      synchronizes with any allocation call that allocates all or part of the
      region <d:emphasis role="italic">p</d:emphasis>. This synchronization
      occurs after any access of <d:emphasis role="italic">p</d:emphasis> by
      the deallocating function, and before any such access by the allocating
      function.
    </d:para>
    <d:sect2>
      <d:title>The aligned_alloc function</d:title>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Synopsis</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:programlisting role="CLexer"><![CDATA[#include <stdlib.h>
void *aligned_alloc(size_t alignment, size_t size);]]>
      </d:programlisting>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Description</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>aligned_alloc</d:code> function allocates space for an
        object whose alignment is specified by <d:code>alignment</d:code>,
        whose size is specified by <d:code>size</d:code>, and whose value is
        indeterminate. The value of <d:code>alignment</d:code> shall be a valid
        alignment supported by the implementation and the value of
        <d:code>size</d:code> shall be an integral multiple of
        <d:code>alignment</d:code>.
      </d:para>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Returns</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>aligned_alloc</d:code> function returns either a null
        pointer or a pointer to the allocated space.
      </d:para>
    </d:sect2>
    <d:sect2>
      <d:title>The calloc function</d:title>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Synopsis</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:programlisting role="CLexer"><![CDATA[#include <stdlib.h>
void *calloc(size_t nmemb, size_t size);]]>
      </d:programlisting>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Description</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>calloc</d:code> function allocates space for an array of
        <d:code>nmemb</d:code> objects, each of whose size is
        <d:code>size</d:code>. The space is initialized to all bits
        zero.<d:footnote><d:para>Note that this need not be the same as the
        representation of floating-point zero or a null pointer
        constant.</d:para></d:footnote>
      </d:para>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Returns</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>calloc</d:code> function returns either a null pointer or a
        pointer to the allocated space.
      </d:para>
    </d:sect2>
    <d:sect2>
      <d:title>The free function</d:title>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Synopsis</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:programlisting role="CLexer"><![CDATA[#include <stdlib.h>
void free(void *ptr);]]>
      </d:programlisting>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Description</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>free</d:code> function causes the space pointed to by
        <d:code>ptr</d:code> to be deallocated, that is, made available for
        further allocation. If <d:code>ptr</d:code> is a null pointer, no
        action occurs. Otherwise, if the argument does not match a pointer
        earlier returned by a memory management function, or if the space has
        been deallocated by a call to <d:code>free</d:code> or
        <d:code>realloc</d:code>, the behavior is undefined.
      </d:para>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Returns</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>free</d:code> function returns no value.
      </d:para>
    </d:sect2>
    <d:sect2>
      <d:title>The malloc function</d:title>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Synopsis</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:programlisting role="CLexer"><![CDATA[#include <stdlib.h>
void *malloc(size_t size);]]>
      </d:programlisting>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Description</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>malloc</d:code> function allocates space for an object
        whose size is specified by <d:code>size</d:code> and whose value is
        indeterminate.
      </d:para>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Returns</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>malloc</d:code> function returns either a null pointer or a
        pointer to the allocated space.
      </d:para>
    </d:sect2>
    <d:sect2>
      <d:title>The realloc function</d:title>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Synopsis</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:programlisting role="CLexer"><![CDATA[#include <stdlib.h>
void *realloc(void *ptr, size_t size);]]>
      </d:programlisting>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Description</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>realloc</d:code> function deallocates the old object
        pointed to by <d:code>ptr</d:code> and returns a pointer to a new
        object that has the size specified by <d:code>size</d:code>. The
        contents of the new object shall be the same as that of the old object
        prior to deallocation, up to the lesser of the new and old sizes. Any
        bytes in the new object beyond the size of the old object have
        indeterminate values.
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        If <d:code>ptr</d:code> is a null pointer, the <d:code>realloc</d:code>
        function behaves like the <d:code>malloc</d:code> function for the
        specified size. Otherwise, if <d:code>ptr</d:code> does not match a
        pointer earlier returned by a memory management function, or if the
        space has been deallocated by a call to the <d:code>free</d:code> or
        <d:code>realloc</d:code> function, the behavior is undefined. If memory
        for the new object cannot be allocated, the old object is not
        deallocated and its value is unchanged.
      </d:para>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Returns</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>        
        The <d:code>realloc</d:code> function returns a pointer to the new
        object (which may have the same value as a pointer to the old object),
        or a null pointer if the new object could not be allocated.
      </d:para>
    </d:sect2>
  </d:sect1>
  <d:sect1>
    <d:title>Communication with environment</d:title>
    <d:sect2 id="abort">
      <d:title>The abort function</d:title>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Synopsis</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:programlisting role="CLexer"><![CDATA[#include <stdlib.h>
_Noreturn void abort(void);]]>
      </d:programlisting>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Description</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>abort</d:code> function causes abnormal program termination
        to occur, unless the signal <d:code>SIGABRT</d:code> is being caught
        and the signal handler does not return. Whether open streams with
        unwritten buffered data are flushed, open streams are closed, or
        temporary files are removed is implementation-defined. An
        implementation-defined form of the status <d:emphasis
        role="italic">unsuccessful termination</d:emphasis> is returned to the
        host environment by means of the function call
        <d:code>raise(SIGABRT)</d:code>.
      </d:para>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Returns</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>abort</d:code> function does not return to its caller.
      </d:para>
    </d:sect2>
    <d:sect2>
      <d:title>The atexit function</d:title>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Synopsis</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:programlisting role="CLexer"><![CDATA[#include <stdlib.h>
int atexit(void (*func)(void));]]>
      </d:programlisting>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>atexit</d:code> function registers the function pointed to
        by <d:code>func</d:code>, to be called without arguments at normal
        program termination.<d:footnote><d:para>The <d:code>atexit</d:code>
        function registrations are distinct from the
        <d:code>at_quick_exit</d:code> registrations, so applications may need
        to call both registration functions with the same
        argument.</d:para></d:footnote> It is unspecified whether a call to the
        <d:code>atexit</d:code> function that does not happen before the
        <d:code>exit</d:code> function is called will succeed.
      </d:para>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Environmental
      limits</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The implementation shall support the registration of at least 32
        functions.
      </d:para>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Returns</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>atexit</d:code> function returns zero if the registration
        succeeds, nonzero if it fails. 
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        <d:emphasis role="bold">Forward references:</d:emphasis> <d:xref
        linkend="at_quick_exit" />, <d:xref linkend="exit" />.
      </d:para>
    </d:sect2>
    <d:sect2 id="at_quick_exit">
      <d:title>The at_quick_exit function</d:title>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Synopsis</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:programlisting role="CLexer"><![CDATA[#include <stdlib.h>
int at_quick_exit(void (*func)(void));]]>
      </d:programlisting>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Description</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>at_quick_exit</d:code> function registers the function
        pointed to by <d:code>func</d:code>, to be called without arguments
        should <d:code>quick_exit</d:code> be called.<d:footnote><d:para>The
        <d:code>at_quick_exit</d:code> function registrations are distinct from
        the <d:code>atexit</d:code> registrations, so applications may need to
        call both registration functions with the same
        argument.</d:para></d:footnote> It is unspecified whether a call to the
        <d:code>at_quick_exit</d:code> function that does not happen before the
        <d:code>quick_exit</d:code> function is called will succeed.
      </d:para>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Environmental
      limits</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The implementation shall support the registration of at least 32
        functions.
      </d:para>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Returns</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>at_quick_exit</d:code> function returns zero if the registration
        succeeds, nonzero if it fails. 
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        <d:emphasis role="bold">Forward references:</d:emphasis> <d:xref linkend="quick_exit" />.
      </d:para>
    </d:sect2>
    <d:sect2 id="exit">
      <d:title>The exit function</d:title>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Synopsis</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:programlisting role="CLexer"><![CDATA[#include <stdlib.h>
_Noreturn void exit(int status);]]>
      </d:programlisting>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Description</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>exit</d:code> function causes normal program termination to
        occur. No functions registered by the <d:code>at_quick_exit</d:code>
        function are called. If a program calls the <d:code>exit</d:code>
        function more than once, or calls the <d:code>quick_exit</d:code>
        function in addition to the <d:code>exit</d:code> function, the
        behavior is undefined.
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        First, all functions registered by the <d:code>atexit</d:code> function
        are called, in the reverse order of their
        registration,<d:footnote><d:para>Each function is called as many times
        as it was registered, and in the correct order with respect to other
        registered functions.</d:para></d:footnote> except that a function is
        called after any previously registered functions that had already been
        called at the time it was registered. If, during the call to any such
        function, a call to the <d:code>longjmp</d:code> function is made that
        would terminate the call to the registered function, the behavior is
        undefined.
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        Next, all open streams with unwritten buffered data are flushed, all
        open streams are closed, and all files created by the
        <d:code>tmpfile</d:code> function are removed.
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        Finally, control is returned to the host environment. If the value of
        status is zero or <d:code>EXIT_SUCCESS</d:code>, an
        implementation-defined form of the status <d:emphasis
        role="italic">successful termination</d:emphasis> is returned. If the
        value of <d:code>status</d:code> is <d:code>EXIT_FAILURE</d:code>, an
        implementation-defined form of the status <d:code>unsuccessful
        termination</d:code> is returned. Otherwise the status returned is
        implementation-defined.
      </d:para>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Returns</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>exit</d:code> function cannot return to its caller.
      </d:para>
    </d:sect2>
    <d:sect2 id="_Exit">
      <d:indexterm>
        <d:primary>_Exit function</d:primary>
      </d:indexterm>
      <d:title>The _Exit function</d:title>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Synopsis</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:programlisting role="CLexer"><![CDATA[#include <stdlib.h>
_Noreturn void _Exit(int status);]]>
      </d:programlisting>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Description</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>_Exit</d:code> function causes normal program termination
        to occur and control to be returned to the host environment. No
        functions registered by the <d:code>atexit</d:code> function, the
        <d:code>at_quick_exit</d:code> function, or signal handlers registered
        by the <d:code>signal</d:code> function are called. The status returned
        to the host environment is determined in the same way as for the
        <d:code>exit</d:code> function (7.22.4.4). Whether open streams with
        unwritten buffered data are flushed, open streams are closed, or
        temporary files are removed is implementation- defined.
      </d:para>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Returns</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>_Exit</d:code> function cannot return to its caller.
      </d:para>
    </d:sect2>
    <d:sect2>
      <d:title>The getenv function</d:title>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Synopsis</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:programlisting role="CLexer"><![CDATA[#include <stdlib.h>
char *getenv(const char *name);]]>
      </d:programlisting>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Description</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>getenv</d:code> function searches an <d:emphasis
        role="italic">environment list</d:emphasis>, provided by the host
        environment, for a string that matches the string pointed to by
        <d:code>name</d:code>. The set of environment names and the method for
        altering the environment list are implementation-defined. The
        <d:code>getenv</d:code> function need not avoid data races with other
        threads of execution that modify the environment
        list.<d:footnote><d:para>Many implementations provide non-standard
        functions that modify the environment list.</d:para></d:footnote>
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        The implementation shall behave as if no library function calls the
        <d:code>getenv</d:code> function.
      </d:para>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Returns</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>getenv</d:code> function returns a pointer to a string
        associated with the matched list member. The string pointed to shall
        not be modified by the program, but may be overwritten by a subsequent
        call to the <d:code>getenv</d:code> function. If the specified
        <d:code>name</d:code> cannot be found, a null pointer is returned.
      </d:para>
    </d:sect2>
    <d:sect2 id="quick_exit">
      <d:title>The quick_exit function</d:title>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Synopsis</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:programlisting role="CLexer"><![CDATA[#include <stdlib.h>
_Noreturn void quick_exit(int status);]]>
      </d:programlisting>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Description</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>quick_exit</d:code> function causes normal program
        termination to occur. No functions registered by the
        <d:code>atexit</d:code> function or signal handlers registered by the
        <d:code>signal</d:code> function are called. If a program calls the
        <d:code>quick_exit</d:code> function more than once, or calls the
        <d:code>exit</d:code> function in addition to the
        <d:code>quick_exit</d:code> function, the behavior is undefined. If a
        signal is raised while the <d:code>quick_exit</d:code> function is
        executing, the behavior is undefined.
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>quick_exit</d:code> function first calls all functions
        registered by the <d:code>at_quick_exit</d:code> function, in the
        reverse order of their registration,<d:footnote><d:para>Each function
        is called as many times as it was registered, and in the correct order
        with respect to other registered functions.</d:para></d:footnote>
        except that a function is called after any previously registered
        functions that had already been called at the time it was
        registered. If, during the call to any such function, a call to the
        <d:code>longjmp</d:code> function is made that would terminate the call
        to the registered function, the behavior is undefined.
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        Then control is returned to the host environment by means of the
        function call <d:code>_Exit(status)</d:code>.
      </d:para>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Returns</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>quick_exit</d:code> function cannot return to its caller.
      </d:para>
    </d:sect2>
    <d:sect2>
      <d:title>The system function</d:title>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Synopsis</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:programlisting role="CLexer"><![CDATA[#include <stdlib.h>
int system(const char *string);]]>
      </d:programlisting>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Description</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        If <d:code>string</d:code> is a null pointer, the
        <d:code>system</d:code> function determines whether the host
        environment has a <d:emphasis role="italic">command
        processor</d:emphasis>. If <d:code>string</d:code> is not a null
        pointer, the <d:code>system</d:code> function passes the string pointed
        to by <d:code>string</d:code> to that command processor to be executed
        in a manner which the implementation shall document; this might then
        cause the program calling <d:code>system</d:code> to behave in a
        non-conforming manner or to terminate.
      </d:para>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Returns</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        If the argument is a null pointer, the <d:code>system</d:code> function
        returns nonzero only if a command processor is available. If the
        argument is not a null pointer, and the <d:code>system</d:code>
        function does return, it returns an implementation-defined value.
      </d:para>
    </d:sect2>
  </d:sect1>
  <d:sect1>
    <d:title>Searching and sorting utilities</d:title>
    <d:para>
      These utilities make use of a comparison function to search or sort
      arrays of unspecified type. Where an argument declared as <d:code>size_t
      nmemb</d:code> specifies the length of the array for a function,
      <d:code>nmemb</d:code> can have the value zero on a call to that
      function; the comparison function is not called, a search finds no
      matching element, and sorting performs no rearrangement. Pointer
      arguments on such a call shall still have valid values, as described in
      (&#xa7; iso.7.1.4).
    </d:para>
    <d:para>
      The implementation shall ensure that the second argument of the
      comparison function (when called from <d:code>bsearch</d:code>), or both
      arguments (when called from <d:code>qsort</d:code>), are pointers to
      elements of the array.
      <d:footnote>
        <d:para>That is, if the value passed is
        <d:code>p</d:code>, then the following expressions are always
        nonzero:
        <d:programlisting role="CLexer"><![CDATA[((char *)p - (char *)base) % size == 0
(char *)p >= (char *)base
(char *)p < (char *)base + nmemb * size]]>
        </d:programlisting>
        </d:para>
      </d:footnote> The first argument when called from
      <d:code>bsearch</d:code> shall equal <d:code>key</d:code>.
    </d:para>
    <d:para>
      The comparison function shall not alter the contents of the array. The
      implementation may reorder elements of the array between calls to the
      comparison function, but shall not alter the contents of any individual
      element.
    </d:para>
    <d:para>
      When the same objects (consisting of <d:code>size</d:code> bytes,
      irrespective of their current positions in the array) are passed more
      than once to the comparison function, the results shall be consistent
      with one another. That is, for <d:code>qsort</d:code> they shall define a
      total ordering on the array, and for <d:code>bsearch</d:code> the same
      object shall always compare the same way with the key.
    </d:para>
    <d:para>
      A sequence point occurs immediately before and immediately after each
      call to the comparison function, and also between any call to the
      comparison function and any movement of the objects passed as arguments
      to that call.
    </d:para>
    <d:sect2>
      <d:title>The bsearch function</d:title>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Synopsis</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:programlisting role="CLexer"><![CDATA[#include <stdlib.h>
void *bsearch(const void *key, const void *base,
              size_t nmemb, size_t size,
              int (*compar)(const void *, const void *));]]>
      </d:programlisting>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Description</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>bsearch</d:code> function searches an array of
        <d:code>nmemb</d:code> objects, the initial element of which is pointed
        to by <d:code>base</d:code>, for an element that matches the object
        pointed to by <d:code>key</d:code>. The size of each element of the
        array is specified by size.
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        The comparison function pointed to by <d:code>compar</d:code> is called
        with two arguments that point to the <d:code>key</d:code> object and to
        an array element, in that order. The function shall return an integer
        less than, equal to, or greater than zero if the <d:code>key</d:code>
        object is considered, respectively, to be less than, to match, or to be
        greater than the array element. The array shall consist of: all the
        elements that compare less than, all the elements that compare equal
        to, and all the elements that compare greater than the
        <d:code>key</d:code> object, in that order.<d:footnote><d:para>In
        practice, the entire array is sorted according to the comparison
        function.</d:para></d:footnote>
      </d:para>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Returns</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>bsearch</d:code> function returns a pointer to a matching
        element of the array, or a null pointer if no match is found. If two
        elements compare as equal, which element is matched is unspecified.
      </d:para>
    </d:sect2>
    <d:sect2>
      <d:title>The qsort function</d:title>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Synopsis</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:programlisting role="CLexer"><![CDATA[#include <stdlib.h>
void qsort(void *base, size_t nmemb, size_t size,
           int (*compar)(const void *, const void *));]]>
      </d:programlisting>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Description</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>qsort</d:code> function sorts an array of
        <d:code>nmemb</d:code> objects, the initial element of which is pointed
        to by <d:code>base</d:code>. The size of each object is specified by
        <d:code>size</d:code>.
      </d:para>
      <d:para>        
        The contents of the array are sorted into ascending order according to
        a comparison function pointed to by <d:code>compar</d:code>, which is
        called with two arguments that point to the objects being compared. The
        function shall return an integer less than, equal to, or greater than
        zero if the first argument is considered to be respectively less than,
        equal to, or greater than the second.
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        If two elements compare as equal, their order in the resulting sorted
        array is unspecified.
      </d:para>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Returns</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>qsort</d:code> function returns no value.
      </d:para>
    </d:sect2>
  </d:sect1>
  <d:sect1>
    <d:title>Integer arithmetic functions</d:title>
    <d:sect2>
      <d:title>The abs, labs and llabs functions</d:title>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Synopsis</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:programlisting role="CLexer"><![CDATA[#include <stdlib.h>
int abs(int j);
long int labs(long int j);
long long int llabs(long long int j);]]>
      </d:programlisting>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Description</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>abs, labs</d:code> and <d:code>llabs</d:code> functions
        compute the absolute value of an integer <d:code>j</d:code>. If the
        result cannot be represented, the behavior is
        undefined.<d:footnote><d:para>The absolute value of the most negative
        number cannot be represented in twos complement.</d:para></d:footnote>
      </d:para>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Returns</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>abs, labs</d:code> and <d:code>llabs</d:code>, functions
        return the absolute value.
      </d:para>
    </d:sect2>
    <d:sect2>
      <d:title>The div, ldiv and lldiv functions</d:title>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Synopsis</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:programlisting role="CLexer"><![CDATA[#include <stdlib.h>
div_t div(int numer, int denom);
ldiv_t ldiv(long int numer, long int denom);
lldiv_t lldiv(long long int numer, long long int denom);]]>
      </d:programlisting>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Description</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>div, ldiv</d:code> and <d:code>lldiv</d:code>, functions
        compute <d:code>numer / denom</d:code> and <d:code>numer %
        denom</d:code> in a single operation.
      </d:para>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Returns</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>div, ldiv</d:code> and <d:code>lldiv</d:code> functions
        return a structure of type <d:code>div_t, ldiv_t</d:code> and
        <d:code>lldiv_t</d:code>, respectively, comprising both the quotient
        and the remainder. The structures shall contain (in either order) the
        members <d:code>quot</d:code> (the quotient) and <d:code>rem</d:code>
        (the remainder), each of which has the same type as the arguments
        <d:code>numer</d:code> and <d:code>denom</d:code>. If either part of
        the result cannot be represented, the behavior is undefined.
      </d:para>
    </d:sect2>
  </d:sect1>
  <d:sect1 id="mbwc_conv_funv">
    <d:title>Multibyte/wide character conversion functions</d:title>
    <d:para>
      The behavior of the multibyte character functions is affected by the
      <d:code>LC_CTYPE</d:code> category of the current locale. For a
      state-dependent encoding, each function is placed into its initial
      conversion state at program startup and can be returned to that state by
      a call for which its character pointer argument, <d:code>s</d:code>, is a
      null pointer. Subsequent calls with <d:code>s</d:code> as other than a
      null pointer cause the internal conversion state of the function to be
      altered as necessary. A call with s as a null pointer causes these
      functions to return a nonzero value if encodings have state dependency,
      and zero otherwise.<d:footnote><d:para>If the locale employs special
      bytes to change the shift state, these bytes do not produce separate wide
      character codes, but are grouped with an adjacent multibyte
      character.</d:para></d:footnote> Changing the <d:code>LC_CTYPE</d:code>
      category causes the conversion state of these functions to be
      indeterminate.
    </d:para>
    <d:sect2>
      <d:title>The mblen function</d:title>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Synopsis</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:programlisting role="CLexer"><![CDATA[#include <stdlib.h>
int mblen(const char *s, size_t n);]]>
      </d:programlisting>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Description</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        If <d:code>s</d:code> is not a null pointer, the <d:code>mblen</d:code>
        function determines the number of bytes contained in the multibyte
        character pointed to by <d:code>s</d:code>. Except that the conversion
        state of the <d:code>mbtowc</d:code> function is not affected, it is
        equivalent to
        <d:programlisting role="CLexer"><![CDATA[mbtowc((wchar_t *)0, (const char *)0, 0);
mbtowc((wchar_t *)0, s, n);]]>
        </d:programlisting>
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        The implementation shall behave as if no library function calls the
        <d:code>mblen</d:code> function.
      </d:para>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Returns</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        If <d:code>s</d:code> is a null pointer, the <d:code>mblen</d:code>
        function returns a nonzero or zero value, if multibyte character
        encodings, respectively, do or do not have state-dependent
        encodings. If <d:code>s</d:code> is not a null pointer, the
        <d:code>mblen</d:code> function either returns 0 (if <d:code>s</d:code>
        points to the null character), or returns the number of bytes that are
        contained in the multibyte character (if the next <d:code>n</d:code> or
        fewer bytes form a valid multibyte character), or returns 1 (if they
        do not form a valid multibyte character).
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        <d:emphasis role="bold">Forward references:</d:emphasis> <d:xref
        linkend="mbrtowc" />.
      </d:para>
    </d:sect2>
    <d:sect2>
      <d:title>The mbtowc function</d:title>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Synopsis</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:programlisting role="CLexer"><![CDATA[#include <stdlib.h>
int mbtowc(wchar_t * restrict pwc,
           const char * restrict s,
           size_t n);]]>
      </d:programlisting>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Description</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        If <d:code>s</d:code> is not a null pointer, the
        <d:code>mbtowc</d:code> function inspects at most <d:code>n</d:code>
        bytes beginning with the byte pointed to by <d:code>s</d:code> to
        determine the number of bytes needed to complete the next multibyte
        character (including any shift sequences). If the function determines
        that the next multibyte character is complete and valid, it determines
        the value of the corresponding wide character and then, if
        <d:code>pwc</d:code> is not a null pointer, stores that value in the
        object pointed to by <d:code>pwc</d:code>. If the corresponding wide
        character is the null wide character, the function is 
        left in the initial conversion state.
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        The implementation shall behave as if no library function calls the
        <d:code>mbtowc</d:code> function.
      </d:para>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Returns</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        If <d:code>s</d:code> is a null pointer, the <d:code>mbtowc</d:code>
        function returns a nonzero or zero value, if multibyte character
        encodings, respectively, do or do not have state-dependent
        encodings. If <d:code>s</d:code> is not a null pointer, the
        <d:code>mbtowc</d:code> function either returns 0 (if
        <d:code>s</d:code> points to the null character), or returns the number
        of bytes that are contained in the converted multibyte character (if
        the next <d:code>n</d:code> or fewer bytes form a valid multibyte
        character), or returns 1 (if they do not form a valid multibyte
        character).
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        In no case will the value returned be greater than n or the value of
        the <d:code>MB_CUR_MAX</d:code> macro.
      </d:para>
    </d:sect2>
    <d:sect2>
      <d:title>The wctomb function</d:title>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Synopsis</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:programlisting role="CLexer"><![CDATA[#include <stdlib.h>
int wctomb(char *s, wchar_t wc);]]>
      </d:programlisting>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Description</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>wctomb</d:code> function determines the number of bytes
        needed to represent the multibyte character corresponding to the wide
        character given by <d:code>wc</d:code> (including any shift sequences),
        and stores the multibyte character representation in the array whose
        first element is pointed to by <d:code>s</d:code>(if <d:code>s</d:code>
        is not a null pointer). At most <d:code>MB_CUR_MAX</d:code> characters
        are stored. If <d:code>wc</d:code> is a null wide character, a null
        byte is stored, preceded by any shift sequence needed to restore the
        initial shift state, and the function is left in the initial conversion
        state.
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        The implementation shall behave as if no library function calls the
        <d:code>wctomb</d:code> function.
      </d:para>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Returns</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        If <d:code>s</d:code> is a null pointer, the <d:code>wctomb</d:code>
        function returns a nonzero or zero value, if multibyte character
        encodings, respectively, do or do not have state-dependent
        encodings. If <d:code>s</d:code> is not a null pointer, the
        <d:code>wctomb</d:code> function returns 1 if the value of
        <d:code>wc</d:code> does not correspond to a valid multibyte character,
        or returns the number of bytes that are contained in the multibyte
        character corresponding to the value of <d:code>wc</d:code>.
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        In no case will the value returned be greater than the value of the
        <d:code>MB_CUR_MAX</d:code> macro.
      </d:para>
    </d:sect2>
  </d:sect1>
  <d:sect1 id="mbwc_str_conv_func">
    <d:title>Multibyte/wide string conversion functions</d:title>
    <d:para>
      The behavior of the multibyte string functions is affected by the
      <d:code>LC_CTYPE</d:code> category of the current locale.
    </d:para>
    <d:sect2>
      <d:title>The mbstowcs function</d:title>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Synopsis</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:programlisting role="CLexer"><![CDATA[#include <stdlib.h>
size_t mbstowcs(wchar_t * restrict pwcs,
                const char * restrict s,
                size_t n);]]>
      </d:programlisting>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Description</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>mbstowcs</d:code> function converts a sequence of multibyte
        characters that begins in the initial shift state from the array
        pointed to by <d:code>s</d:code> into a sequence of corresponding wide
        characters and stores not more than <d:code>n</d:code> wide characters
        into the array pointed to by <d:code>pwcs</d:code>. No multibyte
        characters that follow a null character (which is converted into a null
        wide character) will be examined or converted. Each multibyte character
        is converted as if by a call to the <d:code>mbtowc</d:code> function,
        except that the conversion state of the <d:code>mbtowc</d:code>
        function is not affected.
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        No more than <d:code>n</d:code> elements will be modified in the array
        pointed to by <d:code>pwcs</d:code>. If copying takes place between
        objects that overlap, the behavior is undefined.
      </d:para>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Returns</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        If an invalid multibyte character is encountered, the
        <d:code>mbstowcs</d:code> function returns
        <d:code>(size_t)(-1)</d:code>. Otherwise, the <d:code>mbstowcs</d:code>
        function returns the number of array elements modified, not including a
        terminating null wide character, if any.<d:footnote
        id="fn_mbtowcs"><d:para>The array 
        will not be null-terminated if the value returned is
        <d:code>n</d:code>.</d:para></d:footnote>
      </d:para>
    </d:sect2>
    <d:sect2>
      <d:title>The wcstombs function</d:title>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Synopsis</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:programlisting role="CLexer"><![CDATA[#include <stdlib.h>
size_t wcstombs(char * restrict s,
                const wchar_t * restrict pwcs,
                size_t n);]]>
      </d:programlisting>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Description</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        The <d:code>wcstombs</d:code> function converts a sequence of wide
        characters from the array pointed to by <d:code>pwcs</d:code> into a
        sequence of corresponding multibyte characters that begins in the
        initial shift state, and stores these multibyte characters into the
        array pointed to by <d:code>s</d:code>, stopping if a multibyte
        character would exceed the limit of <d:code>n</d:code> total bytes or
        if a null character is stored. Each wide character is converted as if
        by a call to the <d:code>wctomb</d:code> function, except that the
        conversion state of the <d:code>wctomb</d:code> function is not
        affected.
      </d:para>
      <d:para>
        No more than <d:code>n</d:code> bytes will be modified in the array
        pointed to by <d:code>s</d:code>. If copying takes place between
        objects that overlap, the behavior is undefined.
      </d:para>
      <d:para><d:emphasis role="bold">Returns</d:emphasis></d:para>
      <d:para>
        If a wide character is encountered that does not correspond to a valid
        multibyte character, the <d:code>wcstombs</d:code> function returns
        <d:code>(size_t)(-1)</d:code>. Otherwise, the <d:code>wcstombs</d:code>
        function returns the number of bytes modified, not including a
        terminating null character, if any.<d:footnoteref
        linkend="fn_mbtowcs"></d:footnoteref>
      </d:para>
    </d:sect2>
  </d:sect1>
</d:chapter>
