<d:chapter version="5.0" xmlns:d="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <?xml-stylesheet href="../css/style.css" type="text/css"?>
    <?dbhtml filename="su/index.html" ?>
    <d:title>Structures and Unions</d:title>
    <d:indexterm>
      <d:primary>structures</d:primary>
    </d:indexterm>
    <d:indexterm>
      <d:primary>unions</d:primary>
    </d:indexterm>
    <d:para>So far what we have seen are data types defiend by the language
    itself. However, there are times when these simple types are not
    enough. For this C has defined two types which can be defined by the user
    or programmer. The two keywords are struct and union. A structure or union
    is basically a composite type. These may consist of one more types of
    C. That is they may contain one or more basic types like int, char etc or
    other structures or unions. Consider following examples:</d:para>
    <d:programlisting role="CLexer">struct {
  int i;
  char c;
  int* p;
  char* s;
} mystruct;

struct {
  int x;
  struct mystruct S;
  } another_struct;

union {
  int i;
  char c;
  int* p;
  char8 s;
} myunion;

union {
  int x;
  union myunion S;
} another_union;</d:programlisting>
<d:para>As you see from the declarations there is no difference between
structures and unions. However, there is a subtle difference. Consider
following program:</d:para>
<d:programlisting role="CLexer">// Author: Shiv Shankar Dayal
// Description: Difference between strutures and unions.

#include &lt;stdio.h>

typedef struct {
  int i;
  double d;
} mystruct;

typedef union {
  int i;
  double d;
} myunion;

int main()
{
  mystruct s;
  myunion u;

  printf("Size of structure is %d\n", sizeof(s));
  printf("Size of union is %d\n", sizeof(u));

  return 0;
}</d:programlisting>
and the output is:
<d:screen>Size of structure is 12
Size of union is 8</d:screen>
<d:para>Before explaining the output let me tell you this that using typedef is
mandatory here to get the <d:code>sizeof</d:code> operator working. If you try
something like <d:code>sizeof(struct mystruct);</d:code> then you will get this
as error. <d:code>invalid application of sizeof to incomplete type struct
mystruct.</d:code> However, you can use an object of <d:code>struct
mystruct</d:code>.</d:para>
<d:indexterm>
  <d:primary>typedef</d:primary>
</d:indexterm>
<d:para>By using <d:code>typedef</d:code> we let the compiler recognize them as
complete types. Now let us see the output. Size of structure is simple. It is
equal to size of an integer plus size of a double. However, size of union is
equal to size of double. Basically, size of a structure is equal to size of all
its elements. For unions size of union is equal to size of biggest
element. This means that elements for a union overlap on the same memory
area. We can use this fact to write a very clever program. Before writing the
program let me give you some background.</d:para>
<d:para>There is something called endianness of a machine. What it means that
how bytes are stored. If a machine is little endian like most intel processors
then the bytes are stoerd in reverse order. What this means that they are not
in there natural order. On big endian machines like PPC architecture the bytes
are in natural order. In other words if the least significant byte of an
integer is stored at the lowest memory address then it is called
little-endian. If the least significant byte is stored at the highest address
then it is called big-endian. For example my machine is intel so let us see
what output we get from this program.</d:para>
<d:programlisting role="CLexer">//Author: Shiv S. Dayal
//Description: Demo of endianness,

#include &lt;stdio.h>

typedef union {
  short int i;
  char c;
} myunion;

int main()
{
  myunion u;

  u.i = 258;

  printf("%d\n", u.c);

  return 0;
}</d:programlisting>
and the output is:
<d:screen>2</d:screen>
<d:para>So as you can see the extra 2 i.e. 258 - 256 is getting stored in
c. Now 2 is the high order byte. Hence we can conclude that my machine is
little-endian.</d:para>
<d:para>More ways to initialize a structure are given below:</d:para>
<d:programlisting role="CLexer">//Author: Shiv S. Dayal
//Description: Structure initialization

#include &lt;stdio.h>

typedef struct {
  short int i;
  char c;
} mystruct;

int main()
{
  mystruct s1 = {34, 'c'}, s2;

  s2.i = 43;
  s2.c = 'e';

  printf("%d %d %c %c\n", s1.i, s2.i, s1.c, s2.c);

  return 0;
}</d:programlisting>
and the output is:
<d:screen>34 43 c e</d:screen>
<d:sect1>
  <d:indexterm>
    <d:primary>pointer members of structures</d:primary>
  </d:indexterm>
  <d:title>Pointer members of a Structure</d:title>
  <d:para>Sometime structures will contain pointer members. Obviously, you will
  have to allocate memory to them or point them to some existing variable’s
  address. Let us see how this is done.</d:para>
  <d:programlisting role="CLexer">//Author:Shiv S. Dayal
//Descrition: Pointer members of a structure

#include &lt;stdio.h>
#include &lt;stdlib.h>

int main()
{
  typedef struct {
    int* i;
    int j;
  }s;

  s* s1;

  s1 = (s*)malloc(sizeof(s));
  s1->i=(int*)4;
  s1->j=5;

  printf("s1->i=%p s1->j=%d\n", s1->i, s1->j);

  return 0;
}</d:programlisting>
and the output is:
<d:screen>s1->i=0x4 s1->j=5</d:screen>
<d:para>You might be wondering why I have casted (<d:code>int*</d:code>) to 4
and used a <d:code>%p</d:code> format specifier. The reason is
<d:code>*i</d:code> is a pointer to an interger and hence
<d:code>s1->i</d:code> is a pointer and will accept only an integer
pointer. Therefore, casting is mandatory else you will get a warning. Again, at
the time of assignment I have assigned value 4 which is an address
actully. Therefore <d:code>%p</d:code> is needed for conversion. However, this
program is a bad, wrong program to death. The reason is the address 4 may be
out of program’s segmenst and touching it in the sense of trying to read from
it or write to it may doom your day. Try to burn your hands. Let us see the
correct version.</d:para>
<d:programlisting role="CLexer">//Author:Shiv S. Dayal
//Descrition: Pointer members of a structure

#include &lt;stdio.h>
#include &lt;stdlib.h>

int main()
{
  typedef struct {
    int* i;
    int j;
  }s;

  s* s1;

  s1 = (s*)malloc(sizeof(s));
  s1->i = (int*)malloc(sizeof(int));
  *(s1->i) = 4;
  s1->j = 5;

  printf("s1->i = %d s1->j = %d\n", *(s1->i), s1->j);

  return 0;
}</d:programlisting>
and the output is:
<d:screen>s1->i=4 s1->j=5</d:screen>
</d:sect1>
<d:sect1>
  <d:indexterm>
    <d:primary>usage of structures</d:primary>
  </d:indexterm>
  <d:indexterm>
    <d:primary>usage of unions</d:primary>
  </d:indexterm>
  <d:title>Usage of Structures and Unions</d:title>
  <d:para>A structure can be used to represent rather complex entities. For
  example, a car. Consider a car. It has weight, power, cost, mileage etc. All
  this can be combined and represented as a structure. Structures can be
  categorized in two categories. One will be normal structures and second is
  seld-referential structures. Self-referential structures contain a pointer to
  a structure of its own type. You will see its usage in the book when we deal
  with data structures. We have already shown you normal structures. The data
  members of a structure are referenced using . operator or -> if they are
  pointer type as we have already seen. The rule of using structures or unions
  is simple. When you cannot represent any entity using provided data types
  then combine the basic entities and use them in an structure or union. Union
  has one distiction which you already know. Consider you know that your entity
  can have multiple type of values but only one at a time. Then you can use
  unions.</d:para>
  <d:para>Structures and unions can be nested as well. I will just give a
  simple example and leave rest to your imagination and previously told
  facts.</d:para>
  <d:programlisting role="CLexer">#include &lt;stdio.h>

typedef struct {
  int j;
}t;

typedef struct{
  int i;
  t t1;
}s;

int main()
{
  s s1;

  s1.i=4;
  s1.t1.j=5;

  printf("%d %d", s1.i, s1.t1.j);

return 0;
}</d:programlisting>
and the output is:
<d:screen>4 5</d:screen>
</d:sect1>
<d:sect1>
  <d:indexterm>
    <d:primary>structures and arrays</d:primary>
  </d:indexterm>
  <d:title>Structures and Arrays</d:title>
  <d:para>There are two posiibilities here. Structures containing arrays and
  arrays of structure. Let us see an example which combines both:</d:para>
  <d:programlisting role="CLexer">//Author: Shiv S. Dayal
//Description: Arrays as structure elements

#include &lt;stdio.h>

typedef struct {
  int i[2];
}ais;

int main()
{
  ais a[2];

  a[0].i[0] = 1;
  a[0].i[1] = 2;
  a[1].i[0] = 3;
  a[1].i[1] = 4;

  printf("%d %d %d %d\n", a[0].i[0], a[0].i[1], a[1].i[0], a[1].i[1]);

  return 0;
}</d:programlisting>
and the output is:
<d:screen>1 2 3 4</d:screen>
</d:sect1>
</d:chapter>
